--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制: 暮雨潇潇   招募Q号: 76846146
FX平方 DX
Mod f-x-square, d-x.
下次上课前请做完
So please finish Percival for next time.
我知道你们中很多人大学时都学过 但复习一下也无妨
I know many of you had this as undergraduates, but it won't hurt to brush up.
谢谢 史蒂芬
Thank you, Steven.
走廊黑板上有高级傅立叶算式
I also put an advanced Fourier system on the main hallway chalkboard.
希望学期结束前有人会解
I'm hoping that one of you might prove it by the end of the semester.
解出来的人不只有好成绩...
Now the person to do so will not only be in my good graces...
还可因此纪录名利双收...
but also go on to fame and fortune...
他的成绩记录和大名...
by having their accomplishment recorded and their name printed...
将流传于麻省理工学院
in the auspicious M.I.T. Tech.
之前解答包括诺贝尔奖得主 菲尔兹奖得主...
Former winners include Nobel laureates, Field's medal winners...
天文物理学家 还有卑贱的麻省理工教授
renowned astrophysicists and lowly M.I.T. professors.
就这样 如果有问题...
Well, that's all. If you have any questions...
我相信汤姆会解答
I'm sure that Tom has the answers.
威尔
Hi, Will.
- 克里斯汀 你好吗? - 很好 你呢?
- Kirsten, how you doing? - I'm all right. How are you?
- 好 - 我昨晚没上凯西
- Good. - I didn't get on Cathy last night.
- 没有? - 没有
- No? - No.
- 为什么? - 不知道
- Why not? - I don't know.
- 凯西! - 干嘛?
- Cathy! - What?
为什么不像平时那样...
Why didn't you give me none of that nasty little hoochie-woochie...
- 让我爽歪歪? - 去你的...
- you usually throw at me? - Oh, fuck you...
还有你的爱尔兰脏话
and your Irish curse, Chuckie.
我才不要吃饱饭为了你的小老二张开腿
Like I'd waste my energy spreading my legs for that Tootsie Roll dick?
- 回家自己打手枪去吧 - 小老二!
- Go home and give it a tug yourself. - Tootsie Roll!
小老二!
T-Toots!
她少一颗牙 威尔
She's missing a tooth, Will.
她皮肤也有问题 我...
She's got skin problems. I don't...
况且到头来摩根八成会娶她 你知道我什么意思?
Plus, it's like 5-to-2 Morgan ends up marrying her, you know what I mean?
朋友的准老婆只能上几次
There's only so many times you can bang your friend's future wife.
错了 你去哪?
It's wrong. Where you going?
- 我要走了 - 我操 才十点就要走?
- I'm gonna take off. - Fuck you, you're taking off. It's, like, what, 10:00?
我累了
No, I'm tired.
爱尔兰脏话?
Irish curse?
她懂什么 根本没有爱尔兰脏话
She don't know. There are'nt no Irish curse.
别老故意打到我
Out! Stop pressuring me back.
不要再靠近本垒板! 是哪一样?
Stop crowding the plate! Which one will it be?
你会被起诉 你知道吗?
You're gonna get charged, you know that?
你以为我怕你啊? 是你他妈的太靠近本垒板
You think I'm afraid of you, you big fuck? You're crowding the fucking plate.
盖西下礼拜会在哈佛的酒吧 我们应该去
Hey, uh, Casey's bouncing up a bar at Harvard next week. We should go up there.
- 到那边干嘛? - 不知道
- What are we gonna do up there? - I don't know.
去整聪明小孩 你很擅长
We'll fuck up some smart kids. Probably fit right in.
臭痞子
Ow! Fucking punk.
- 怎样? 你很凶吗? - 来啊!
- Oh, what's up? You still tough? - Come on!
来啊 对 约翰 来啊
Come on. Come on. That's it.
(麻省理工学院校友会)
I'd hold you forever here
In my arms
- 蓝勃教授? - 有何贵干?
- Professor Lambeau? - Yes?
我是你的应用理论课学生 我们都是数学和科技学院的
I'm in your applied theories class. We're all up at the math and science building.
过来 今天礼拜六
Come here. It's Saturday.
- 除非你今晚陪我喝酒 - 或许吧
- Unless you wanna have a drink with me tonight. - Maybe.
但我们急着想弄清楚
We just couldn't wait until Monday to find out.
- 弄清楚什么? - 是谁解出傅立叶算式
- Find out what? - Who proved the theorem.
完全正确 谁解的?
This is correct. Who did this?
- 杰克? - 不是我
- Jack? - It wasn't me.
- 尼米许? - 不可能
- Nemesh? - N-No way.
- 快点 乔依 快跑! - 比利 麦克马拉要上了
- Come on, Joey, now! - Billy, McNamara's up.
放马过来 小子!
Come on, kid!
- 乔依 拿下! 拿下! - 杂种!
- Joey, dig it out! Dig it out! - Son of a bitch!
快放下 麦克! 这样才对! 做得好! 二垒 往二垒跑
Bring it down, Mac! That's how to do it! Attaboy! Take two, Mac.
摩根 穿条纹裤的俏屁股女人是谁? 那屁股真不赖
Hey, Morgan, who's the girl with the striped pants? She's got a nice ass.
- 嗯 屁股不赖 - 她跟谁一起?
- Yeah, that's a real nice ass. - Who's the guy she's with?
是他妈的卡迈 我讨厌他 威尔认识他
That fucking guinea. I hate that little bitch. Will knows him.
是的 他妈的卡迈
Yeah, I do. Yeah, fucking Carmine Scarpaglia.
- 他幼稚园时把我揍得好惨 - 那个人?
- That guy used to beat the shit out of me in kindergarten. - That guy?
嗯
Yeah. Mm-hmm.
操他妈的 去弄点东西吃吧
Fuck this. Let's get some food.
- 摩根 你不跟她讲话吗? - 去她的
- Oh, what, Morgan, you're not gonna go talk to her? - Fuck her.
- 我宁可吃大汉堡 - 到"凯利"去吧
- I could go for a Whopper. - Let's go to Kelly's.
我才不要去 你只是喜欢那儿的外卖女孩
Morgan, I'm not going to Kelly's just because you like the take-out girl.
- 而且要多绕15分钟路 - 那他妈的有什么事可以做? 挪不出15分钟吗?
- It's 15 minutes out of our way. - What the fuck are we gonna do? We can't spare 15 minutes?
大汉堡
Double burger.
查克 我有点大汉堡
Chuck, I had a double burger.
闭嘴! 我知道你点什么
Would you shut the fuck up! I know what you ordered. I was there.
- 那就把我的三明治给我 - 什么叫你的三明治? 是我买的
- So give me my fucking sandwich. - What do you mean, your sandwich? I bought it.
摩根 你身上有多少钱?
Morgan, how much money you got on you?
买霜淇淋就会有零钱了嘛
I said I'd get change when I get the snow cone.
停车后 把汉堡给我 别这么讨厌
I said that when we pulled up. Give me my sandwich and stop being a prick.
好 把身上的一毛六给我
All right, well, give me your fucking 16 cents that you got on you now.
我让你他妈的分期付款买汉堡 汉堡摆这边
We'll put your fucking sandwich on layaway. Here we go. Keep it right up here for ya.
让你分期付款 每天六分钱
We'll put you on a program. Every day you come in here with your six cents.
- 周末给你汉堡 - 你怎么这么恶劣?
- At the end of the week, you get your sandwich. - Are you gonna be an asshole?
你他妈的以为我卖慈济汉堡啊? 你应该建立良好信用
What am I, fucking sandwich welfare? I think you should establish a good line of credit.
对 就像你们买沙发那样... 分期付款
Like how you bought your couch... payment plans.
记得你妈每天存十块钱吗
Remember how your mother brought in ten dollars every day for a year.
最后她终于买到沙发了
She finally got her couch Rent-A-Center style.
- 可以把食物给我了吗? - 把你的大汉堡拿去
- Can I have my food, please? - Here's your fucking double burger.
- 哇! - 等等 查克
- Whoa! - Hey, hold up, Chuck.
- 慢下来 - 怎么了?
- Slow it down. - Who do we got?
- 还不知道 - 傻帽!
- I don't know yet. - Hey, douche bag!
你 你个混蛋!
Yeah, you, you skank face!
- 他妈的闭嘴 - 下去 - 你担心什么?
- Shut the fuck up. - Get outta here. - What are you worried about?
你要舔舔我的小鸡巴吗?
Why don't you lick my love stick?
15分钟前才在公园看到他 当时就该扁他了 现在是吃零食的时间
We seen the guy 15 minutes ago. We should've fight him then. We're eating our snacks now.
- 闭嘴 摩根 你也下去 - 我才不去 - 那就别去
- Shut up, Morgan, you're going. - I'm not going. - So don't go.
- 我不去 - 你他妈的给我去 摩根
- I'm not going. - Fucking go, Morgan.
我跟你讲 两秒内不滚出去
Let me tell you something. If you're not out there in two fucking seconds,
等我扁完他们 就扁你
when I'm done with them, you're next.
卡迈 是我 威尔 记得吗 我们是幼稚园同学
Carmine, it's me, Will. Remember, we went to kindergarten together.
Way down the street there's a light in his place
He opens the door, he's got that look on his face
- 妈的 快走 兄弟 - 踩烂他的脸
- Fucking, let's go, man. - Step on his fucking head.
让他屁股着地 叫那家伙住手 混蛋
Get his ass on the ground. Stop that motherfucker.
混蛋 去死吧!
Motherfucker, die!
- 卡特! - 快走!
- Carter! - Come on!
威尔! 威尔 快走!
Will! Will, come on!
威尔 条子 快走 快走
Will, come on. Let's go. Let's go.
别激动 别激动
Easy, brother, easy.
- 谢谢你们出来 - 过来!
- Hey, fellas, thanks for coming out. - Come here!
哇! 哇!
Whoa! Whoa!
操
Ah. Fuck.
我这是做梦 还是班级变大了?
Is it just my imagination, or has my class grown considerably?
不出意料的话...
Well, by no stretch of my imagination...
你们是来听我讲课
do I believe you've all come here to hear me lecture.
或想知道神秘数学奇才是谁
Rather, to ascertain the identity of the mystery math magician.
别再不告而别 沉默的天才 出来领奖吧
So without further adieu, come forward, silent rogue, and receive thy prize.
抱歉让观众失望了 但是...
Well, I'm sorry to disappoint my spectators, but...
看来今天不会揭晓了
it seems there will be no unmasking here today.
我和同事决定再下战帖
However, uh, my colleagues and l have conferred,
外面黑板上有个题目...
and there is a problem on the board right now...
我们花了两年时间才解开
that took us more than two years to prove.
请沉默的天才再解解看
So let this be said: The gauntlet has been thrown down,
全体教授已备有解答
but the faculty have answered and answered with vigor.
几时提讯?
Hey, when's the arraignment?
下星期
Next week.
对不起
Sorry.
- 你在做什么? - 对不起
- What are you doing? - Sorry.
那是别人的劳动 你不能在人家的方程式上涂鸦
That's people's work. You can't graffiti here.
- 你别走! - 去你的!
- Don't you walk away from me! - Hey, fuck you!
别耍聪明 你叫什么名字?
Oh, you're a clever one. What's your name?
我的天
Oh, my God.
好像是对的
Looks right.
要多智障才会被开除?
Will, how retarded do you gotta be to get fired from that job?
我是说 在屋子里扫地有那么难吗?
I mean, how hard is it to push a motherfucking broom around?
麦琪 你连扫地都会被开除
Mitch, you got fired from pushing a fucking broom.
那是因为管理阶层重组
I got fired because management was restructuring.
对 重组智障儿的数量
Yeah, restructuring the amount of retards they had working for them.
闭嘴 你被开除的次数更多
Shut up. You get canned more than tuna, bitch.
起码现在我有工作 不是吗?
At least I got a motherfucking job right now, don't I?
- 威尔 你为何被开除? 快说 - 管理阶级重组
- Why'd you get fired, Will? Come on. - Management was restructuring.
- 我舅舅或许能给你工作 - 他可以帮我吗?
- My uncle could probably get you on a demo team. - Can he do that?
你耍我! 我昨天还问过你
You kidding me! I asked you yesterday if I could get a job.
我昨天告诉你"不行"
And I told you "no" yesterday.
- 怎么样 盖斯? - 怎么样 盖斯? - 怎么样 盖斯?
- What's up, Casey? - What's up, Case? - What's up, Big Case?
坐这边
Let's sit over here.
好的 走吧
All right. Let's go.
这就是... 这就是哈佛酒吧?
Oh, this is... this is a Harvard bar, huh?
我以为墙上会有方程式呢
I thought there'd be, like, equations and shit on the wall.
我要一壶店里最好的啤酒
I will take a pitcher of the finest lager in the house.
暂停 我要去泡吧台的哈佛辣妹
Timeout. I'm gonna have to bust a little move on them Harvard hotties down there at the bar.
- 干得漂亮点 - 帮我们也钓几个
- Work some magic. - Get some potion for us.
- 哈罗 - 哈罗
- Oh, hello. - Oh, hello.
- 你好吗? - 好
- Hi. How are ya? - Fine.
- 那么 两位美女... - 常来吗?
- So, do you ladies, uh... - Come here often?
我常来吗? 我很少到这里
Do I come here? I come here a bit.
你知道 我只是偶尔来
I'm here, you know, from time to time.
- 你们在这儿念书? - 对
- Do you go to school here? - Yep.
- 就是嘛 我想我跟你同班 - 是吗 哪一班?
- Yeah, that's it. I think I had a class with you. - Oh, yeah. What class?
- 历史 - 或许
- History. - Maybe.
应该没错
Yes, I think that's what it was.
你可能... 不记得我 你知道 我喜欢这里
You don't necessarily... may not remember me. You know, I like it here.
- 我来这边并不表示我是天才 但我还是很聪明 - 嘿
- It doesn't mean because I go here, I'm a genius. I am very smart. - Hey.
- 过的怎样? 你好吗? - 好 你呢?
- Hey, how's it going? How are ya? - Good. How ya doing?
你说你在哪一班?
What class did you say that was?
- 历史 - 对
- History. - Yeah.
单单历史? 那一定是概论课程
Just history? It must have been a survey course then.
- 对 是概论课程 - 好的
- Yeah, it was. It was surveys. - Right.
你应该上上看 不错的课程 不错的班级
You should check it out. It's a good course. It'd be a good class.
- 你觉得那堂课怎么样? - 老实说
- How'd you like that course? - You know, frankly,
- 我觉得相当基础 - 基础
- I found that class, you know, rather elementary. - Elementary.
- 肯定是的 - 嗯
- You know, I don't doubt that it was. - Yeah.
我记得那堂课了
I, uh, I remember that class.
就... 就在休息和午餐之间
It was, um... It was just between recess and lunch.
克拉克 你走开啦
Clark, why don't you go away?
- 放轻松点 - 走开啦
- Why don't you relax? - Why don't you go away?
- 我跟我的新朋友很开心 - 有什么问题吗?
- I'm just having fun with my new friend. - Are we gonna have a problem?
不 不 不 没问题
No, no, no, no. There's no problem here.
只是想请教你对于市场经济...
I was just hoping you might give me some insight into the evolution...
在南部殖民地发展的看法
of the market economy in the southern colonies.
我主张在革命战争前...
My contention is that prior to the Revolutionary War, the economic modalities...
南方殖民地的经济形态...
especially in the southern colonies...
最适合被刻画为...
could most aptly be characterized as...
- 农地 - 让我跟你说两句
- agrarian precapitalist. - Let me tell you something.
那当然是你的论点 新生嘛
Of course that's your contention. You're a first-year grad student.
才刚念完马克思主义... 也许念到皮特 盖瑞森...
You just got finished reading some Marxian historian... Pete Garrison, probably...
下个月念到雷蒙的论点 你会更深信不疑
You're gonna be convinced of that till next month when you get to James Lemon.
然后你会谈到维吉尼亚州及宾夕法尼亚州...
Then you're gonna be talking about how the economies of Virginia and Pennsylvania...
在1740年如何企业化与资本主义化
were entrepreneurial and capitalist way back in 1740.
一直持续到明年你反刍伍德
That's gonna last until next year. You're gonna be in here regurgitating Gordon Wood,
大谈革命前乌托邦...
talking about, you know, the prerevolutionary utopia...
和军事动员对资本形成的影响
and the capital-forming effects of military mobilization.
事实上我反对这个观点
Well, as a matter of fact, I won't,
因为伍德完全低估了...
because Wood drastically underestimates the impact of...
伍德低估了社会财富的差异...
Wood drastically underestimates the impact of social distinctions...
尤其是继承财富
predicated upon wealth, especially inherited wealth.
这是你从维克斯读到的论点 "艾群就业分析" 98页 对吗?
You got that from Vickers' Work in Essex County. Page 98, right?
我也读过 你要剽窃整本书吗?
I read that too. Were you gonna plagiarize the whole thing for us?
对这些论点你有个人想法吗?
Do you have any thoughts of your own on this matter?
你动过脑子吗? 你跑到酒吧来 高谈书中的论点
Or is that your thing? You come into a bar. You read some obscure passage.
还假装... 是自己的观点
Then pretend... pawn it off as your own.
就为了泡妞 糗我朋友吗?
As your own idea just to impress some girls? Embarrass my friend?
可悲的是在五十年后
See, the sad thing about a guy like you is, in 50 years,
你才会开始了解
you're gonna start doing some thinking on your own.
生命中有两件事是确定的
You're gonna come up with the fact that there are two certainties in life.
一: 是别只会打高空
One: Don't do that.
二: 你花一万五所受的教育...
And two: You dropped 150 grand on a fucking education...
用一块五就能在图书馆得到
you could've got for $1.50 in late charges at the public library.
对 但我会有文凭
Yeah, but I will have a degree,
你却只能在我去滑雪胜地途中卖薯条给我的小孩
and you'll be serving my kids fries at a drive through on our way to a skiing trip.
或许吧 起码我不会没创意
Maybe, but at least I won't be unoriginal.
不爽的话可以到外面解决
If you have a problem with that, we could step outside. We could figure it out.
不 没事 很酷
No, man, there's no problem. It's cool.
- 酷? - 对
- It's cool? - Yeah.
- 对 - 你他妈的酷毙了
- Cool. - Damn right, it's cool.
现在喜欢我了吧?
How do you like me now?
那小子聪明绝顶
My boy's wicked smart.
才来三分钟就摆平一个傻蛋 嗯哼?
I just spent three minutes in this fucking place and run into a barney, huh?
有了
There it is.
- 你好 - 他们不错
- Nice to meet you. - They were fine, man.
我们差点就要把到她们 结果比利... 触怒到她们当中一人...
I was gonna close the deal, but then Chuck... Billy insulted one of them...
辣妹就说我头快秃了 人又太胖
The heavyset girl said I had a receding hairline, and I was a few pounds overweight.
我就说"去你妈的"
And I was, like, "Go fuck yourself."
我什么都没说
I swallowed a bug.
嗨
Hi.
- 你是个白痴 - 什么?
- You're an idiot. - What?
你是个白痴 我坐在那边45分钟...
You're an idiot. I've been sitting over there for 45 minutes...
等你过来跟我讲话
waiting for you to come and talk to me.
但我累了 我得回家了
But I'm tired now, and I have to go home.
我不能再坐着等你
I couldn't sit there anymore waiting for you.
- 我是威尔 - 史凯兰
- I'm Will. - Skylar.
- 史凯兰 - 对了
- Skylar. - Oh, and by the way,
那个人... 迈可波顿二号...
that guy over there... Michael Bolton clone...
跟我们不是一国的
He wasn't sitting with us, so to speak.
- 我知道 我看得出来 - 好的
- I know. I kinda got that impression. - Good. Okay.
我得走了
Well, I've got to go.
我要早起花钱买文凭
Gotta get up early and waste some more money on my overpriced education.
- 我不是指你 - 没关系
- No, I didn't mean you. - That's all right.
这是我的电话 也许有空可以喝杯咖啡
There's my number. Maybe we can go out for coffee sometime.
好 或许聚在一起吃焦糖
All right, yeah. Maybe we can just get together and eat a bunch of caramels.
- 什么意思? - 想想看
- What do you mean? - When you think about it,
- 那和喝咖啡一样惬意 - 是吗 好吧
- it's as arbitrary as drinking coffee. - Oh. Yeah. Okay.
那好
Uh, right, then.
得了 你在开玩笑
Oh, come on. You're kidding.
哟!
Yo!
- 去你的! - 我才去你的
- Fuck you, bitch! - Fuck you.
- 那些傻屌在那边 - 等等
- There goes them fucking barneys right now with his skiing trip. - Hold on.
我们应该扁那个混蛋
We should've beat that old bitch's ass.
你喜欢青苹果甜甜圈吗?
Do you like apples?
- 喜欢 - 喜欢?
- Yeah. - Yeah?
我得到她的电话了! 你却只能吃甜甜圈
Well, I got her number! How do you like them apples?
We arrived tonight
The miles were over me
I turned off the light
So, come on, night
Everyone who's gone
Home to oblivion
So come home
So come on by
Come.
打扰了 这是大楼管理室吗?
Excuse me? Is this the Buildings and Grounds office?
是的 有何贵干?
Yeah. What can I do for you?
我要找个在这里打工的学生
I just need the name of a student who works here.
- 没学生替我做事 - 请你查一下好吗?
- No students work for me. - Could you please check?
有个人在我那栋楼做事
I have this guy who works in my building.
- 个子大概这么高 - 你是哪栋楼?
- He's about this high. - Which one is your building?
- 二栋 - 二栋
- Two. - Two. Building two.
- 如果有东西失窃 我该知道 - 不是那样
- Look, if anything was stolen, I should know about it. - No, it's nothing like that.
我只是要找他
I just need his name.
- 除非你投诉 否则不能告诉你 - 这位是蓝勃教授
- I can't give you his name unless you have a complaint. - This is Professor Lambeau.
这位是海斯教授
And this is Professor Hayes.
汤姆 拜托
Tom, please.
这很重要
This is important. Please.
他今天没上班
Will didn't show for work today.
他透过PO找到这份工作 你可以找到他
Got this job through his P.O. You can call him.
- PO? - 对 观护人
- P.O.? - Yeah. Parole officer.
谢谢
Thank you.
混蛋
Asshole.
法官先生 这溯及1789年的司法判例
There is a lengthy legal precedent, Your Honor, going back to 1789,
被告可对政府单位要求自卫权...
whereby a defendant can claim self-defense against an agent of the government...
如果该举动是为保护自由 抗拒暴政制裁的话
if that act is deemed a defense against tyranny, a defense of liberty.
法官先生 1887年比彻尔
Your Honor, Henry Ward Beecher,
- 曾在普利茅斯讲道坛引述过... - 1887?
- in Proverbs from the Plymouth Pulpit, 1887, said, quote... - 1887?
- 怎么了 - 现在都20世纪了
- Excuse me. - This is the 20th century.
- 他在嘲弄法庭 - 宪法赋与我
- He's gonna make a mockery. - I am afforded the right to speak in my own defense, sir,
为自己辩护之权
by the Constitution of the United States.
- 别跟我扯宪法 - 宪法保障了我的自由
- Don't tell me about the Constitution. - This guarantees my liberty.
"自由" 也许你淡忘了 是一个人呼吸的权利
"Liberty," in case you've forgotten, is a soul's right to breathe.
无法让人呼吸的法律太严肃
When it cannot take a long breath, laws are girded too tight.
- 不自由 人就是"行尸走肉" - 什么?
- Without liberty, man is a syncope. - Man is a what?
- 出处同前 法官先生 - 轮到我了
- Ibid., Your Honor. - Son, my turn.
我在这坐了十分钟看着你的罪状
I've been sitting here for ten minutes now looking over this rap sheet of yours.
我不敢相信 93年6月袭击罪
I just can't believe it. June '93, assault.
93年9月袭击罪
September '93, assault.
94年2月偷车罪
Grand theft auto, February of '94.
你引述"马与马车的财产权"...
Where, apparently, you defended yourself and had the case thrown out by citing...
并以自我辩护让此案驳回
"free property rights of horse and carriage" from 1798.
95年1月 扮成警察
Joke. January '95, impersonating an officer.
伤害 窃盗 拒捕 全部驳回
Mayhem, theft, resisting. All overturned.
我知道你住过几个寄养家庭
I'm also aware that you've been through several foster homes.
因受虐而从其中三个搬出
The state removed you from three because of serious physical abuse.
别的法官是关心你 但你打警察 就得坐牢
You know, another judge might care, but you hit a cop. You're going in.
不准提出抗告 保释金五万
Motion to dismiss is denied. $50,000 bail.
谢谢
Thank you.
起立
Rise.
- 喂? - 史凯兰?
- Hello? - Uh, Skylar?
- 嗯 - 我是威尔
- Yep. - Hey, uh, it's Will.
- 谁? - 我是威尔
- Who? - It's Will.
你前两天在酒吧碰到的幽默有形的帅哥
You know, the really funny, good-looking guy you met at the bar the other night.
我不记得有碰到这样的人 我想起来了
I don't recall meeting anyone who matches that description. I think I'd remember.
好吧 是那个丑陋无比又没牙...
Oh, all right, you got me. It's the ugly, obnoxious, toothless loser...
还整夜缠着你不放的废物
who got hammered and wouldn't leave you alone all night.
威尔! 我记起来了
Oh, Will! I remember.
你好吗? 我还在想你会不会打来
How are you? I was wondering if you'd call me.
- 我一直在想... - 怎么样 宝贝?
- Yeah, look, I was wondering... - Yo, what's up, baby?
- 稍等 - 你要怎样? 宝贝 想上我吗?
- Hold on one second. - What you doing? Want some of my ass?
- 赫芙 我记得在少年监狱见过你 你好吗? - 干嘛?
- Herve, I remember you from juvi. How you doing? - What you doing?
对不起
Oh, yeah, sorry about that.
我在想也许这礼拜可以聚一聚
I was wondering maybe we could get together sometime this week.
- 坐在咖啡座 吃点焦糖 - 听起来很棒
- Sit out at a cafe. Maybe have some caramels. - Oh, that sounds wonderful.
- 可以吗? - 可以 你在哪里?
- Yeah? - Yeah, sure. Where are you?
我站的地方有点糟
Uh, well, actually, this is just a shot in the dark,
你那儿总不会是看守所吧?
but, uh, there's no chance that you're pre-law, is there?
- 坐 - 谢谢
- Have a seat. - Thank you.
很高兴跟你讲话
Nice talking to ya.
你他妈的想干嘛?
What the fuck do you want?
我是杰洛蓝勃
I'm Gerald Lambeau.
你叫他滚蛋的那个教授
Professor you told to fuck himself.
你他妈找我干嘛?
Well, what the fuck do you want?
我跟法官谈过 他同意在我监护之下放你出去
I've spoken to the judge, and he's agreed to release you under my supervision.
- 真的? - 是的
- Really? - Yeah.
- 但有两个条件 - 哪两个?
- Under two conditions. - What are those?
第一个条件 你每周要跟我碰面
First condition is that you meet with me every week.
- 做什么? - 和你讨论数学
- What for? - Go over the proof you're working on,
给你做些更高级的...
get into some more advanced...
组合数学
combinatorial mathematics,
有限数学
finite math.
好像很有趣
Sounds like a real hoot.
第二个条件...
And the second condition is that...
你要看心理医生
that you see a therapist.
由我每周负责作评估报告
I'm responsible to submit reports on those meetings.
如果你不及格 照样送你回来坐牢
If you fail to meet with any of those conditions, you will have to serve time.
好 数学我接受 但我不看去他的心理医生
All right. I'll do the math, but I'm not gonna meet with any fucking therapist.
这总比蹲牢房好 不是吗?
It's better than spending that time in jail, isn't it?
我看过你的书 你提到有个病人麦克的问题...
I read your book, and "Mike" was having the same problems...
事实上和证券营业员查克一样
that "Chad," the stockbroker, was having.
完全正确 说得很准 很好
Absolutely right. Right on the button. Good for you, Will.
- 非常棒 - 谢谢
- Very nice. - Thank you.
威尔 有关压力... 我不是评头论足
Will, the pressures... and I'm not judging them.
也不是武断地贴你标签
I'm not labeling them,
但它破坏了你的潜力
but they are destroying your potential.
别再恶作剧 耍蠢 吹擂
No more shenanigans. No more tomfoolery. No more ballyhoo.
你说得对 天哪 我知道
You're right. God, I know.
要摆脱不容易 来 多讲点
You're not gonna get off that easily. Come on, Will. A bit more.
- 我有做过一些事 知道吗? - 哪... 哪种事?
- Well, I mean, I do do things, you know? - What... What kind of things?
我做过的 你知道 我躲避人群
I do things that, you know, I mean, I hide from people.
- 你躲避? - 不 我是说 我也去一些地方交朋友
- You hide, do you? - No, no. I mean, I like... I go places. I interact.
- 真的? 哪种地方? - 一些酒吧
- Really? What sort of places? - Just certain clubs.
再来 很好 哪种酒吧?
More. That's nice. Yes. What sort of clubs?
像是"幻想"
Like, uh, like Fantasy.
"幻想" 还不错的地方 再多讲点
Fantasy. That's nice. A bit more.
一进去整个人就被音乐包围
It's something like when you get in there, the music, like, owns you.
浩势音乐 就像... 砰 砰 砰
It's like that house music. It's like... Bom, bom, bom
砰-砰-砰 砰 砰 砰 砰
Bom-bom-bom Boom, boom, boom, boom
- 你就会开始跳舞 - 砰 砰 砰 是的
- You know, you start dancing. - Boom, boom, boom. Yeah.
只是...
It's just...
是的
Yes.
隐瞒你是同性恋很难吗?
Do you find it hard to hide the fact that you're gay?
你在说什么? 什么?
What are you talking about? What?
兄弟 两秒前你准备扑向我
Look, buddy, two seconds ago, you were ready to give me a jump.
扑? 你...
A jump? Are you...
很抱歉让你失望了
I'm terribly sorry to disappoint you.
没关系 我不在乎你从后面上
Hey, I don't have a problem with it. I don't care if you putt from the rough.
你在说...从...从后面上你? 你在讲什么?
What are you... P... Putting from the rough? What on earth are you talking about?
困难的定理就像交响曲
A difficult theorem could be like a symphony.
性感无比
It's very erotic.
你找别人 我应付不来
You go somewhere else. I can't handle this.
- 哇 - 谢谢 亨利
- Wow. - Thank you, Henry.
- 啊 亨利 - 嗨 杰洛
- Ah, Henry. - Hi, Gerry.
知道吗? 我不能再做这种公众服务
You know something? I can't do this pro bono work anymore.
- 这... 不值得 - 怎么了?
- It's just not... It's not worth it. - What happened?
下周我要上电视
Well, I'm going on national television next week.
没空告诉你 更别提这个胡言乱语的疯子
I mean, I haven't got time to tell you, much less talk to that raving looney in there.
他简直冥顽不灵
An absolute lunatic, he is.
亨利
Henry.
好 你在你床上
Okay, you are in your bed, Will.
你几岁了?
Now, how old are you?
七岁
Seven.
你看到什么?
What do you see?
我房里有东西
Something's in my room.
是什么?
What is it?
是个... 是个人形 在我头上盘旋
It's like a... It's a figure. It's hovering over me.
你在安全的地方 威尔
You are in a safe place, Will.
他在... 他在摸我
It's t... It's touching me.
他摸你哪里?
Where is it touching you?
摸我那下面
It's touching me down there,
我很紧张
and I'm nervous.
不必紧张 威尔
You don't have to be nervous, Will.
我们开始跳舞
We start dancing and dancing.
好美
It's just beautiful,
因为日落前...
because we can make...
我们可以疯狂地做爱
a lot of love before the sun goes down.
烟火飞舞
Skyrockets in flight
午后欢乐
Afternoon delight
- 嘿 嘿 嘿 烟火飞舞  - 天啊
- Hey, hey, hey, afternoon delight  - Jesus.
午后欢乐 嗒 嗒 嗒 嗒
Skyrockets in flight Da-da-da-da
- 抱歉 瑞克 - 怎样安排时间我自有打算
- I'm sorry, Rich. - I have better things to do with my time.
嘿 嘿 午后欢乐 来! 我们跳舞!
Hey, hey, afternoon delight  Come on! One dance!
你把我催眠了 知道吗?
You really hypnotized me, you know?
- 看在老天份上 威尔 - 干嘛? 他走了 你别怪在我头上
- For God's sake, Will. - What? Oh, come on. He left. You can't pin that on me.
- 你得跟这些人合作 - 凝视...
- I told you to cooperate with these people. - Look...
- 我的眼睛 - 出去 威尔
- into my eyes. - Get out, Will.
我不需要治疗
I don't need therapy.
够了 出去!
That's enough. Get out!
- 我早上打过电话给梅尔... - 有用吗?
- I called Mel Weintraub this morning to see... - Oh, what's the use?
你想怎么做?
What do you want to do?
- 有个人 - 是谁?
- Well, there's someone. - Who is he?
他过去是我的... 我的大学室友
He used to be my, uh... my roommate in college.
邦克山社区大学
信任 在感情上很重要
Trust. Very important in a relationship.
在临床上也很重要
It's also very important in a clinical situation.
为何信任对于突破患者心防...
Why is trust the most important thing...
是最重要的关键?
in making a breakthrough with a client?
莫琳 别老张着嘴 听课
Maureen, stop the oral fixation for a moment and join us.
- 维尼 - 嗯...
- Vinnie. - Um...
因为...
Because, uh...
信任就是... 就是生命
Trust is, uh... Trust is life.
很深奥 谢谢你 维尼
Wow. That's very deep. Thank you, Vinnie.
下次抄你弟弟的笔记
Next time, get the notes from your brother.
若病患不信任你 就不会坦诚相对
If a patient doesn't feel safe enough trust you, then they won't be honest with you.
治疗对他们来说就毫无意义.
Then there's really no point for them being in therapy.
我是说 如果她们不信任你 就不会跟你上床
I mean, hey, if they don't trust you, you're never gonna get them to sleep with you.
那该是心理医生的最终目的 趁脆弱时下手
That should be the goal of any good therapist. Nail them while they're vulnerable.
我的座右铭
That's my motto.
很好 大家都醒了 欢迎回来
Oh, good, everyone's back. Welcome back, everybody.
- 你好 尚恩 - 嗨 杰洛
- Hello, Sean. - Hey, Gerry.
女士们先生们 我们很荣幸请来一位大人物
Um, ladies and gentlemen, we are in the presence of greatness.
杰洛蓝勃教授 组合数学的菲尔兹奖得主
Professor Gerald Lambeau, Fields medal winner for combinatorial mathematics.
- 哈罗 - 谁知道什么是菲尔兹奖?
- Hello. - Anyone know what the Field's medal is?
了不起 数学界的诺贝尔奖
It's a really big deal. It's like the Nobel prize for math.
只是它四年才颁一次 很伟大
Except they only give it out once every four years. It's a great thing.
是惊人的荣耀 今天就到此为止 下课
It's an amazing honor. Okay, everybody, that's it for today.
谢谢 礼拜一见 下次我们谈佛洛伊德
Thanks. We'll see you Monday. We'll be talking about Freud.
他为何用古柯碱杀马 谢谢
Why he did enough cocaine to kill a small horse. Thank you.
- 你好吗? - 真高兴见到你
- How are you? - It's good to see you.
很高兴见到你
Good to see you.
- 尚恩 我有一件你会感兴趣的事 - 是吗?
- Sean, I think I got something interesting for ya. - Yeah?
需要血液和尿液吗? 干嘛?
What, you have to have blood and urine? What's up?
同学会你怎么不来?
Why didn't you come to the reunion?
我... 我在忙
You know, I'm... I've been busy.
- 大家很想你 - 真的?
- You were missed. - Really?
- 我们多久没见面了? - 南茜去世前
- So how long has it been since we've seen each other? - Before Nancy died.
是 很抱歉
Yeah, I'm sorry.
我在巴黎开会 都是那该死的会议
I was in Paris. It was that damn conference.
我收到你寄来的卡片 很好
I got your card. It was nice.
- 过来 - 投得不错
- Come here. - Now that's a takedown.
怎么样? 博得同情没?
Hey, what happened? Did you get leniency or what?
获得保释和一周两次的辅导
I got, uh, probation and then counseling two days a week.
真不是盖的 你伶牙利嘴 快 摩根! 快投球!
Joke. You're a smoothie. Come on, Morgan! Just submit!
比尔 放开他 我们会错过球赛的
Hey, Bill, just-just get off him. We're gonna miss the game.
- 我行程很满 我很忙 - 尚恩 尚恩
- I've got a full schedule. I'm very busy. - Sean, Sean.
这孩子不可思议 前所未见
This-This boy is incredible. I've never seen anything like him.
是什么让他这么不可思议?
What makes him so incredible, Gerry?
- 听过拉玛努强吗? - 听过 没有
- You ever heard of Ramanujan? - Yeah, yeah. No.
他是个男人 活在一百多年前 印度人
It's a man. He lived over 100 years ago. He was Indian.
- 卓越成就 - 卓越成就 嗯
- Dots, not feathers. - Not feathers. Yeah.
他住在茅屋里
He lived in this tiny hut somewhere in India.
没受过正规教育
He had no formal education.
- 无法取得任何科学著述 - 来杯咖啡?
- He had no access to any scientific work. - Coffee?
- 您呢 先生? - 来一点点
- You, sir? - Just a little.
但他偶然发现一本旧数学课本
But he came across this old math book,
从简单的条条框框 他推导出深奥的理论...
and from the simple text, he was able to extrapolate theories...
多年来难倒无数数学家
that had baffled mathematicians for years.
对 连续分数 他是以...
Yes. Continued fractions. He wrote, uh...
- 他寄给剑桥的哈帝 - 嗯 剑桥
- Well, he mailed it to Hardy at Cambridge. - Yeah, Cambridge. Yeah.
- 哈帝即刻了解那是天才之作... - 嗯
- And Hardy immediately recognized the brilliance of his work... - Mm-hmm.
把他带到英国 然后他们合作多年
and brought him over to England, and then they worked together for years,
创造出令人兴奋的数学理论
creating some of the most exciting math theory ever done.
拉玛努强...
This-This Ramanujan...
他的天才无与伦比
his-his genius was unparalleled, Sean.
- 这孩子就像他一样 - 嗯
- Well, this boy's just like that. - Hmm.
- 但他... 有点防御性 - 嗯
- But he's... he's a bit defensive. - Hmm.
我需要有人突破他的心防
I need someone who can get through to him.
- 像是我? - 对 就是你
- Like me? - Yeah, like you.
- 为什么? - 因为你们有相同背景
- Why? - Well, because you have the same kind of background.
- 什么背景? - 你们来自同一个区
- What background? - Well, you're from the same neighborhood.
- 他是南区人? - 是的
- He's from Southie? - Yeah.
南区的天才少年
Boy genius from Southie.
- 你之前找过几个心理医生? - 五个
- How many shrinks you go to before me? - Five.
- 让我猜 拜瑞? 亨利? 没找瑞克吧? - 是的
- Let me guess. Barry? Henry? Not Rick? - Yeah. Yeah.
- 尚恩 请跟他碰面 一周一次就好 - 嗯哼
- Sean, please, just meet with him once a week. - Mm-hmm.
拜托你
Please?
这就像打牌 别让牌泄底
It's a poker game with this kid. Don't let him know what you've got.
要是他碰过你的书 那他或许就已经看过你的书
He probably even read your book, if he could find it.
他要找到很难
It's gonna be hard for him to find.
- 嗨 威尔 - 嗨
- Hi, Will. - Hi.
这是尚恩麦圭尔 威尔杭汀
This is Sean Maguire. Will Hunting.
你好
How are ya?
- 来吧 开始治疗吧 - 好 开始吧
- Yeah. Let's get started. - Yeah, let's do it.
我迫不及待了 快开始疗程
I'm pumped. Let's let the healing begin.
- 请出去一下? - 对 麻烦你 汤姆
- Will you excuse us? - Yeah, please, Tom.
你也出去 杰洛
You, too, Gerry.
好 当然
Yeah, of course.
你好吗?
How are you?
你是南区哪里人?
Where you from in Southie?
- 我喜欢你这边的装潢 - 谢谢
- I like what you've done with the place. - Oh, thanks.
这些书都是零买的?
Do you buy all these books retail,
还是派人买的整套心理丛书?
or do you send away for, like, a "shrink kit" that comes with all these volumes included?
- 你喜欢看书? - 喜欢
- Do you like books? - Yeah.
- 这些书你读过吗? - 不知道
- Did you read any of these books? - I don't know.
- 那些书呢? - 大概没有
- How about any of these books? - Probably not.
顶层那些呢? 看过没?
What about the ones on the top shelf? You read those?
- 看过 - 很好 你有什么感想?
- Yeah, I read those. - Good for you. What do you think about them?
我不是他妈的来做读书报告 那是你的书 你怎么不读?
I'm not here for a fucking book report. They're your books. Why don't you read them?
我读过 非读不可
I did. I had to.
- 一定花了你不少时间 - 是的
- Must've taken you a long time. - Yeah, it did.
美国通史: 第一册
United States of America: A Complete History, Volume l.
天哪 若想看真的历史
Jesus. If you wanna read a real history book,
你应该读辛恩的书
read Howard Zinn's A People's History in the United States.
那本书会让你大吃一惊
That book'll fucking knock you on your ass.
比乔姆斯基的书更好吗?
Better than Chomsky's Manufacturing Consent?
- 你觉得那是本好书? - 我搞不懂你们这些人
- Do you think that's a good book? - You fucking people baffle me.
把钱花在这种他妈的垃圾书上面 还读得津津有味
You spend all your money on these fucking fancy books. You surround yourselves with them.
- 这些是漏洞百出的书 - 什么是漏洞百出的书?
- They're the wrong fucking books. - What are the right fucking books, Will?
- 让你头发竖起来的 - 嗯 我剩的头发不多
- Whatever blows your hair back. - Yeah. Haven't got much hair left.
要是你把烟戒了
Hey, you know you'd be better shoving that cigarette up your ass.
- 可能会健康点 - 我知道
- It'd probably be healthier for you. - Yeah, I know.
- 抽烟妨碍我练瑜珈 - 你运动吗?
- It really gets in the way of my yoga. - You work out, huh?
- 你举重吗? - 嗯
- What, you lift? - Yeah.
- 举重机? - 不 哑铃
- Nautilus? - No, free weights.
- 真的? 哑铃? - 你举多少?
- Oh, really? Free weights, huh? - Yeah. Yeah, big time.
- 是吗? - 就是那样
- Yeah? - Just like that.
- 你举多少? - 285 你呢?
- What do you bench? - 285. What do you bench?
你画的?
You paint that?
- 对 你画画吗? - 不
- Yeah. Do you paint? - Uh-uh.
- 你雕塑吗? - 不
- Do you sculpt? - No.
喜欢艺术吗?
Do you like art?
- 喜欢音乐吗? - 真烂
- Do you like music? - This is a real piece of shit.
告诉我你觉得怎么样
Oh, tell me what you really think.
线条结构复杂混乱
Just the linear and impressionistic mix makes a very muddled composition.
笔法颇有印象派画风 除了有白人在划船
It's also a Winslow Homer rip-off, except you got whitey rowing the boat there.
那倒怪了 我并不想模仿莫内
Well, it's art, Monet. It wasn't very good.
- 我在意的不是那个 - 你在意什么?
- That's not really what concerns me though. - What concerns you?
- 只是色彩 - 你知道这幅画的灵魂是什么?
- Just the coloring. - You know what the real bitch of it is?
这幅画是以数字画的
It's paint-by-number.
以数字上色? 至少这色彩让我着迷
Is it color-by-number? Because the colors are fascinating to me.
- 真的? - 我保证
- Aren't they really? - You bet.
我想你差点就要割耳朵了
I think you're about one step away from cutting your fucking ear off.
- 真的? - 没错
- Really? - Oh, yeah.
那我应该搬到法国改名为"梵高"?
Think I should move to the south of France, change my name to "Vincent"?
- 听过"暴风雨中的港口"吗? - 听过
- You ever heard the saying, "any port in a storm"? - Yeah.
- 也许指的就是你 - 哪方面?
- Yeah, maybe that means you. - In what way?
- 也许你正在暴风雨中 剧烈的暴风雨中 - 可能吧
- Maybe you're in the middle of a storm, a big fucking storm. - Yeah, maybe.
天色昏暗 海浪撞击小船
The sky's falling on your head. The waves are crashing over your little boat.
桨就要断了
The oars are about to snap.
你吓坏了 迫切需要港口
You just piss in your pants. You're crying for the harbor.
你想要脱离其中
So maybe you do what you gotta do to get out.
也许这就是你成为心理医生的原因
You know, maybe you became a psychologist.
答对了 就是这样 让我做事吧 你妨碍我了
Bingo. That's it. Let me do my job now. You start with me. Come on.
- 也许你娶错女人 - 也许你讲话该小心点!
- Maybe you married the wrong woman. - Maybe you should watch your mouth!
小心点 好吗?
Watch it right there, chief, all right?
啊
Ah.
情况就是如此 是吗?
That's it, isn't it?
你娶错女人了
You married the wrong woman.
发生什么事? 她抛弃你了?
What happened? What, did she leave you?
她是不是...搞上别的男人?
Was she, you know... banging some other guy?
再对我太太无礼 我就宰了你
If you ever disrespect my wife again, I will end you.
我会他妈的宰了你
I will fucking end you.
听到没?
Got that, chief?
时间到了
Time's up.
是的
Yeah.
稍息 两位
At ease, gentlemen.
你没事吧?
You okay?
如果你不再想见他 我理解
Look, I'll understand if you don't wanna meet with him again.
星期四下午四点 一定要他来
Thursday, 4:00. Make sure the kid's here.
好
Yeah.
谢谢
Thanks.
你戴那副眼镜好可爱
Well, you look lovely in those glasses.
- 多谢你 - 真漂亮
- Thank you very much. - They're just beautiful.
- 我一直想擦蓝色眼影 - 美极了
- Yes, I always wanted dark blue eye shadow. - Wonderful.
我在英国长大 念贵族学校
Growing up in England, you know, I went to a very nice school.
就是那种积极 有组织 又独立自主的私立学校
You know, it was kind of progressive, organic, do-it-yourself, private school.
然后是很有前途的哈佛医学院
Then Harvard. Hopefully med school.
你知道我发现什么
You know, I figured out, by the end,
最后我的脑子会价值25万美金
my braings gonna be worth $250,000.
听起来很可怕吧?
That sounded horrible, didn't it?
再来一杯"迈泰"!
Bring me another mai tai!
酷 你父母一定很乐于付钱
Yeah, that's cool. I mean, I bet your parents were happy to pay.
错 我自己付 我继承了遗产
No, I was happy to pay. I inherited the money.
那么钱都给哈佛吗?
Wow. Is Harvard getting all that money?
不 给了斯坦福 我六月毕业后到那里深造
No, Stanford. I'm going there in June when I graduate.
所以你只是想利用这个水手啰?
All right, so you just wanted to use this sailor and then run away, huh?
我要先拿你做解剖实验
I was gonna, you know, experiment on you for anatomy class first, obviously.
这样的话 好吧
In that case, that's fine.
- 想看我变魔术吗? - 好啊
- Hey, you wanna see my magic tricks, Skylar? - Of course.
好 保证...
All right. Promise to...
好的
All right.
- 这是给你的 鲁道夫 - 等等 你需要我的魔杖
- This one's for you, Rudolph. - Wait, wait. You need my wand.
好 敲一下 谢谢 好的
All right, give me a hit. Thank you. All right.
我会让这些焦糖消失
I'm gonna make all these caramels disappear.
准备好了吗?
You ready? Ready.
一 二 三
One, two, three.
全不见了
They're all gone.
有兔子的话... 会比较成功
That was my... It works better when I have my rabbit.
那...
Well...
我不常约会
I don't really date, you know, that much.
我认为自己... 多不幸
How very unfortunate... I think for me.
你懂我意思? 我知道你在想什么
You know what I mean? I know you've been thinking about it.
- 我没有 - 我知道你有
- Oh, no, I haven't. - Yes, you have.
- 真的没有 - 你有 你想要睡前一吻
- No, I really haven't. - Yes, you have. You were hoping to get a good night kiss.
不 我想要睡前一炮
No, you know, I tell ya, I was hoping to get a good night laid.
不过我愿意勉强接受一吻
But I'll settle for, like, a kiss, you know?
- 你很高尚 - 谢谢
- How very noble of you. - Thank you.
- 嗯 - 不 我...我真的想要一吻
- Mm. - No, I was... I was hoping for a kiss.
何不现在就解决?
Well, why don't we just get it out of the way now?
- 现在? - 对
- Right now? - Yeah.
来
Come on.
我吃到你的酸黄瓜了
I think I got some of your pickle.
又是你?
You again, huh?
跟我来
Come with me.
现在要干嘛? 这是男人的行家选择?
So what's this? A Taster's Choice moment between guys?
这里真不错 你喜欢天鹅? 这算恋物癖吗?
This is really nice. You got a thing for swans? Is this, like, a fetish?
这是需要花点时间的事吗?
Is it something, like, maybe we need to devote some time to?
- 我在想你批评我画的事 - 噢
- Thought about what you said to me the other day. About my painting. - Oh.
失眠大半夜的思索后
Stayed up half the night thinking about it.
突然我想到一件事
Something occurred to me.
接着就沉沉入睡 不再想你的事
I fell into a deep, peaceful sleep and haven't thought about you since.
- 你知道我当时想到什么吗? - 不知道
- You know what occurred to me? - No.
你只是个孩子 你根本不晓得你在说什么
You're just a kid. You don't have the faintest idea what you're talking about.
- 为什么 谢谢 - 没关系
- Why, thank you. - It's all right.
因你没离开过波士顿
You've never been out of Boston.
是没有
Nope.
所以问你艺术 你可能会...
So if I asked you about art, you'd probably give me the skinny...
提出艺术书籍中的粗浅论调
on every art book ever written.
有关米开朗基罗? 你知道很多
Michelangelo? You know a lot about him.
他的政治抱负 他和教皇
Life's work, political aspirations. Him and the pope.
性倾向 所有作品 对吗?
Sexual orientation. The whole works, right?
但你不知道西斯汀教堂的气味
I bet you can't tell me what it smells like in the Sistine Chapel.
你从没站在那儿观赏美丽的天花板
You never actually stood there and looked up at that beautiful ceiling.
我看过
Seeing that.
如果我问关于女人的事
If I ask you about women,
你八成会说出个人偏好的谬论
you'll probably give me a syllabus of your personal favorites.
你可能上过几次床
You may have even been laid a few times.
但你说不出在女人身旁醒来...
But you can't tell me what it feels like to wake up next to a woman...
那种很幸福的滋味
and feel truly happy.
你是个很倔的孩子
You're a tough kid.
我问战争 你会说莎士比亚的话
I ask you about war, you'd probably throw Shakespeare at me, right?
"共赴战场 亲爱的朋友"
"Once more into the breach, dear friends."
但你从没接近过战争
But you've never been near one.
从没把好友的头抱在膝盖上...
You've never held your best friend's head in your lap...
看着他吐出最后一口气向你呼救
and watch him gasp his last breath looking to you for help.
我若问你爱情 你会引述十四行诗
If I asked you about love, you'd probably quote me a sonnet,
但你从没看过女人的脆弱
but you've never looked at a woman and been totally vulnerable.
她能以双眼击倒你
Known someone that could level you with her eyes.
感觉上帝让天使为你下凡
Feeling like God put an angel on Earth just for you,
她能从地狱救出你
who could rescue you from the depths of hell.
你不了解当她天使的滋味
And you wouldn't know what it's like to be her angel,
拥有对她的爱 直到永远
to have that love for her be there forever.
经历这一切 经历癌症
Through anything. Through cancer.
你无法体会在医院躺两个月...
And you wouldn't know about sleeping sitting up in a hospital room...
握住她的纤纤小手那种感觉
for two months, holding her hand,
因为医生一看到你就知道...
because the doctors could see in your eyes...
会客时间的规定对你无效
that the terms "visiting hours" don't apply to you.
你不了解真正的失去
You don't know about real loss,
因为唯有爱别人胜于自己才能体会
because that only occurs when you love something more than you love yourself.
我怀疑你敢那样爱人
I doubt you've ever dared to love anybody that much.
看着你 我没看到聪明自信
I look at you. I don't see an intelligent, confident man.
我看到被吓傻的狂妄孩子
I see a cocky, scared shitless kid.
但你是天才 没人能否认
But you're a genius, Will. No one denies that.
没人能了解你的深度
No one could possibly understand the depths of you.
但你看我的画就认定了解我
But you presume to know everything about me because you saw a painting of mine.
你把我的人生撕裂了
You ripped my fucking life apart.
你是孤儿 对吧?
You're an orphan, right?
你想我会知道你日子有多苦...
Do you think I'd know the first thing about how hard your life has been...
你的感受 你是谁...
how you feel, who you are...
是因为我看过雾都孤儿吗?
because I read Oliver Twist?
太简化你了吗?
Does that encapsulate you?
我不在乎 因为...
Personally, I don't give a shit about all that, because...
你知道吗? 我对你无从下手...
You know what? I can't learn anything from you...
我不能靠任何书籍认识你
I can't read in some fucking book.
除非你想谈自己
Unless you wanna talk about you,
谈你是谁
who you are.
那我就着迷了 我愿意加入
And I'm fascinated. I'm in.
但你不想那么做 对吗?
But you don't wanna do that, do you, sport?
你怕你会被说出来的话吓到
You're terrified of what you might say.
轮到你说了 大哥
Your move, chief.
喂? 喂?
Hello? Hello?
喂?
Hello?
瓦兰帝教授 又是你吗?
Professor Valenti, are you calling me again?
怪胎
Freak.
- 上帝 - 天哪 你打给谁?
- Oh, God. - Christ, who did you call?
- 没有 我忘了号码 - 你他妈智障?
- No one. I forgot the number. - You fucking retarded?
冒雨打电话 竟忘了号码
You went all the way out there in the rain, and you didn't bring the number.
那是你妈的免费电话
No, it was your mother's 900 number. I just ran out of quarters.
别扯上我妈好不? 我刚上过你妈
Why don't we get off on mothers? I just got off yours.
很好笑 摩根
That's pretty funny, Morgan.
太炫了
That's a fucking nickel, bitch.
- 继续跟我作对看看 - 好的 那么 摩根
- Keep antagonizing me. Watch what happens. - All right, then, Morgan.
- 看看会怎样 - 好的 那么 摩根
- Watch what happens. - All right, then, Morgan.
再整我啊
Keep fucking with me.
不准抽烟
No smoking.
什么叫没讲话? 你在那里一个钟头
What do you mean, he didn't talk? You were in there for an hour.
他就坐着等会谈结束
He just sat there counting the seconds until the session was over.
- 让人印象蛮深刻的 - 他为什么要那么做?
- Pretty impressive, actually. - Why would he do that?
证明他不想讲就不必讲
To prove to me he doesn't have to talk to me if he doesn't want to.
这是小孩玩的瞪人比赛吗?
What is this? Some kind of staring contest between two kids from the old neighborhood?
对 而且我不能先讲话
Yeah, it is, and I can't talk first.
我们知道你的理论 亚历山大 但这孩子找出简单的几何图
We know your theory, Alexander, but the boy's found a simple geometrical picture.
- 树状结构行不通 - 他把两个顶点连起来了
- A tree structure won't work. - Look now. He's joining the two vertices.
但我算出总数
But I can do the sum.
- 那是集合项的方法 - 但是 杰洛
- It's how you group the terms, Alexander. - But, Gerry.
如果这样做...
If we do the whole thing this way, then...
看 看
Hey, look, look.
我写下来了 这样比较简单
I wrote it down. It's simpler this way.
有些人就是走运
Sometimes people get lucky.
你是个聪明的人
You're a brilliant man.
我有一次搭飞机
You know, I was on this plane once,
坐在机上...
and I'm sitting there, and...
机长广播道
the captain gets on, he does his whole, you know,
"飞行于三万五千尺" 但是他放下麦克风后
"we'll be cruising at 35,000 feet," but then he puts the mike down.
- 他忘了把它关掉 - 嗯
- He forgets to turn it off. - Mm-hmm.
他转向副驾驶说
So he turns to the copilot. He's, like,
"我现在很想要口交和咖啡"
"You know, all I could use right now is a fucking blow job and a cup of coffee."
空服员冲去驾驶室...
So the stewardess fucking goes bombing up from the back of the plane...
跟他说麦克风没关
to tell him the microphone's still on.
机尾有个人说 "别忘了咖啡"
This guy in the back of the plane's like, "Hey, hon, don't forget the coffee."
你搭过飞机?
You ever been on a plane?
没有 那只是个笑话 用第一人称比较好笑
No, but it's a fucking joke. It works better if I tell it in the first person.
没错
Yeah, it does.
我做过爱 知道吗?
I have been laid, you know?
真的? 很好
Really? Good for you.
- 我很厉害 - 很厉害?
- Big time, big time. - Big time, huh?
对 我上礼拜有约会
I went on a date last week.
- 怎么样? - 很好
- How'd it go? - It was good.
- 要再约会吗? - 不知道
- Going out again? - I don't know.
- 为什么? - 我没打给她
- Why? - Haven't called her.
- 天哪 你真外行 - 我知道我在干嘛
- Christ, you're an amateur. - I know what I'm doing.
放心 我知道我在干嘛
Yeah. Don't worry about me. I know what I'm doing.
这女孩很漂亮
Yeah, but this girl was, like, you know, beautiful.
她聪明风趣 跟我以前认识的女生不一样
She's smart. She's fun. She's different from most of the girls I've been with.
- 那就打给她 罗密欧 - 让自己发现她并没那么聪明吗
- So call her up, Romeo. - Why, so I can realize she's not that smart.
其实很无聊吗? 我是说 你别...
That she's fucking boring? You know, I mean, you don't...
这女孩现在很完美 我不想破坏这种完美
This girl's, like, fucking perfect right now. I don't wanna ruin that.
或许是你不想破坏你自己的完美
Maybe you're perfect right now. Maybe you don't wanna ruin that.
我觉得那是极好的哲学
But I think that's a super philosophy, Will.
这样可以一辈子不认识任何人
That way, you can go through your entire life without ever having to really know anybody.
我太太一紧张就放屁
My wife used to fart when she was nervous.
她有各种奇妙的小特质
She had all sorts of wonderful idiosyncrasies.
你知道 她睡觉会放屁
You know, she used to fart in her sleep.
抱歉跟你讲这种事
Just thought I'd share that with you.
有天晚上大声到把狗吵醒
One night it was so loud, it woke the dog up.
她醒来说"是你吗?"
She woke up and gone, like, "Was that you?"
我说"是" 我不忍心告诉她 天哪
I said, "Yeah." I didn't have the heart to tell her. Oh, God.
- 她把自己臭醒? - 是的
- She woke herself up? - Yes.
天哪 她去世两年了 而那是我记得的事
Oh, Christ. But, Will, she's been dead two years and that's the shit I remember.
像那样的小事很奇妙
It's wonderful stuff, you know? Little things like that.
那是我最想念的事
Yeah, but those are the things I miss the most.
这些小特质
Those little idiosyncrasies that only I knew about.
让她成为我太太
That's what made her my wife.
她也知道我所有的小瑕疵
Boy, and she had the goods on me too. She knew all my little peccadillos.
人们称之为不完美 其实不然
People call these things "imperfections," but they're not.
那才是好东西
That's the good stuff.
能选择让谁进入我们的世界
And then we get to choose who we let into our weird little worlds.
你并不完美
You're not perfect, sport.
我不吊你胃口
And let me save you the suspense.
你认识的女生也不完美
This girl you met, she isn't perfect either.
问题是你们是否完美地合适
But the question is whether or not you're perfect for each other.
亲密关系就是这么回事
That's the whole deal. That's what intimacy is all about.
你可以知道全世界的事
Now you can know everything in the world, sport,
但发掘的方法唯有去尝试
but the only way you're finding out that one is by giving it a shot.
你不能跟我这个糟老头学
You certainly won't learn from an old fucker like me.
就算我知道 我也不告诉你
Even if I did know, I wouldn't tell a pissant like you.
为什么?
Yeah, why not?
你把其他事都告诉我了 天哪
You told me every other fucking thing. Jesus Christ.
你的话比我所遇到的任何心理医生都多
Fucking talk more than any shrink I ever seen in my life.
我只是教心理学 我说过我不是心理医生
I teach the shit. I didn't say I knew how to do it.
是的
Yeah.
那么你想过再婚吗?
You ever think about getting remarried?
我太太死了
My wife's dead.
- 所以才叫"再婚" - 她死了
- Hence the word "remarried." - She's dead.
我想那是极好的哲学 尚恩
Yeah, well, I think that's a super philosophy, Sean.
这样可以过下半辈子...
I mean, that way, you can actually go through the rest of your life...
而不用认识任何人
without ever really knowing anybody.
时间到了
Time's up.
- 别关 - 好的
- Hold it open. - Okay.
谢谢
Thanks.
I am happy with you
I know I'm about to love you
Yeah, yeah, yeah. You know him
Oh, my, you made me...
G小调 最悲叹的曲调
"G" minor seventh. Saddest of all chords.
- 哈罗 - 嗨
- Hello. - Hey.
- 你去哪里了? - 对不起 我...我很忙...
- Where have you been? - I'm sorry. I've been, like... I've been really busy, and...
- 但是... - 我也是
- But, um... - Mmm. Me too.
我还...以为你会打来
Yeah. I... I thought you'd call.
是...
Yeah, um...
- 我是说 我们相处愉快 - 的确如此
- I mean, we had a really good time. - I had a really good time too.
我是说... 我...
I mean, I just... I...
对不起 我搞砸了
I'm sorry, you know. I blew it.
不 没关系
No. No, I mean, you know, it's all right.
我在想 呃
Yeah, um, so, I was wondering if, uh,
你会不会再让我试一遍
if, you know, you'd give me another crack at it.
我是说 让我再约你出去
You know, let me take you out again.
- 不行 - 好吧
- I can't. - All right.
不 我...我不是说永远不行
Oh, no, I didn't... I didn't mean I can't, like, ever.
只是说现在不行
I just can't right now.
我得做质子光谱分配
I've got to assign the proton spectrum for "ebogamine."
听起来有趣 其实很无聊
All that sounds really, really interesting. It's actually fantastically boring.
- 好吧 呃... - 或许改天吧
- All right, um... - Maybe some other time.
- 那明天呢?- 好啊
- Like tomorrow? - Um, yeah, all right.
- 好的 - 好的
- Okay. - Okay.
- 再见 - 再见
- Bye. - Bye.
你在这儿干嘛?
What are you doing here?
我等不到明天了
I couldn't wait till tomorrow.
你从哪儿弄到这个?
Where the fuck did you get this?
我得跟你同学上床
I had to sleep with someone in your class.
希望是个穿拖鞋又有口臭的人
Oh, I hope it was someone with the open-toed sandals and the really bad breath.
- 走 去找乐子 - 不行 我得念这个
- Come on. Let's go have some fun. - No, I've got to learn this.
你不会明天就要开刀吧?
Well, you're not going into surgery tomorrow, are you?
- 不是 - 走吧
- No. - Let's go.
天啊! 我的狗赢了!
Oh, my God! My dog is winning!
加油 迷雾!
Come on, Misty!
加油! 快跑! 看! 加油!
Come on! Run! Look at that! Come on!
他在那边 迷雾领先! 加油!
Look, there he goes. Misty, run! Come on!
- 我们赢了 - 它完胜对手
- We won. - He totally won.
你在这边长大的吗?
So did you grow up around here then?
不远 南波士顿
Not far. South Boston.
赢了比赛让我脸好热
Still glowing from my win.
看你乐成这样
Look at you. You're so happy.
我的样子还好吧?
And what was that like then?
很正常 没什么特别的
It was normal, I guess. Nothing special.
你有很多兄弟姊妹吗?
Do you got lots of brothers and sisters?
- 你有很多兄弟姊妹吗? - 那是我问你的
- Do I have a lot of brothers and sisters? - That's what I said.
- 我是个天主教徒 你说呢? - 对
- Well, Irish Catholic, what do you think? - Right. That's right.
- 几个? - 告诉你你也不信
- How many? - You wouldn't believe me if I told you.
- 为什么? 说啊 五个? - 不是
- Why? Go on. What? Five? - No.
七个? 八个? 几个?
Seven? Eight? How many?
- 我有十二个哥哥 - 你才没有!
- I have 12 big brothers. - You do not!
我发誓 我是幸运十三
No, I swear to God. I swear to God. I'm lucky 13 right here.
你知道他们的名字吗?
Do you know all their names?
当然知道 他们是我哥哥
Do I... Yeah, they're my brothers.
叫什么名字?
What are they called?
马奇 瑞奇 丹尼 泰瑞 麦奇 大卫 提米 汤米 乔依 罗比 强尼和布莱恩
Marky, Ricky, Danny, Terry, Mikey, Davey, Timmy, Tommy, Joey, Robby, Johnny and Brian.
再说一遍
Say it again.
马奇 瑞奇 丹尼 泰瑞 麦奇 大卫 提米 汤米 乔依 罗比 强尼和布莱恩
Marky, Ricky, Danny, Terry, Mikey, Davey, Timmy, Tommy, Joey, Robby, Johnny and Brian.
还有小威
And Willy.
- 小威? - 对
- Willy? - Yeah.
- 威尔 - 哇
- Will. - Wow.
- 你常和他们见面吗? - 他们都住南区
- Do you still see all of them? - Yeah, well, they all live in Southie.
- 我跟他们中三个人一起住 - 是吗?
- I'm living with three of them right now. - Oh, yeah?
- 是的 - 我好想见他们
- Yeah. - I'd like to meet them.
好 就去见他们
Yeah, we'll do that.
我昨晚读过你的书
Oh, you know, I read your book last night.
原来是你
Oh, so you're the one.
你还辅导退伍军人吗?
Do you still, uh... Do you still counsel veterans?
没有
No, I don't.
- 为什么? - 我太太生病时就没做了
- Why not? - Well, I gave it up when my wife got sick.
你有没有想过若没遇见你太太 你的生活会怎样?
You ever wonder what your life would be like if you, uh, if you never met your wife?
什么? 没有她会不会比较好?
What? Wonder if I'd be better off without her?
- 不 不 不 我没说比较好 - 不
- No, no, no, I'm not saying, like, better off. - No.
- 我没那意思 - 没关系 这是很重要的问题
- I didn't mean it like that. - It's all right. It's an important question.
因为人总会有不好的时候 但这也会让你...
because you'll have bad times, but that'll always wake you up...
回忆起从前不曾在意的好事
to the good stuff you weren't paying attention to.
你不后悔认识你太太?
And you don't regret meeting your wife?
为什么? 因为我现在的痛苦?
Why? because the pain I feel now?
是有遗憾 但我不后悔跟她共度的每一天
Oh, I got regrets, Will, but I don't regret a single day I spent with her.
你几时知道她是理想对象?
So when did you know, like, that she was the one for you?
1975年10月21日
October 21, 1975.
天哪 你他妈的记得日期?
Jesus Christ. You know the fucking day?
对 那是世界大赛第六场 红袜队史上最重大的球赛
Oh, yeah, because it was game six of the World Series, biggest game in Red Sox history.
- 没错 - 我和朋友睡人行道排队买票
- Yeah, sure. - My friends and I had slept out all night to get tickets.
- 你有票? - 对 比赛当天我们坐在酒吧
- You got tickets? - Yep. Day of the game I was sitting in a bar,
等球赛开始 有个女孩走进来
waiting for the game to start and in walks this girl.
那是场很棒的球赛 八局下半
It was an amazing game though. You know, bottom of the eighth, Carbo ties it up.
六比六平手 打到第十二局
It was 6-6. It went to 12.
下半场时矮冬瓜菲克斯上场
Bottom of the 12th, in stepped Carlton Fisk, old Pudge.
他站上本垒 姿势很怪
Steps up to the plate. You know, he's got that weird stance.
- 嗯 嗯 - 然后... 砰! 他把球打击出去
- Yeah, yeah. - And then... Boom! He clocks it, you know.
左外野高飞球!
High fly ball down the left field line!
三万五千人站起来对球吼
Thirty-five thousand people on their feet, yelling at the ball.
这还不算什么 因为菲斯克像发了疯似地挥手说
But that's nothing, because Fisk, he's waving at the ball like a madman.
- 对 我见到过 - "飞过去! 飞过去!
- Yeah, I've seen that. - "Get over! Get over!
- 对 - 飞过去!"
- Right. - Get over!"
结果球飞到边界 三万五千名球迷...
Then it hits the foul pole. He goes ape-shit, and 35,000 fans...
冲到场上
They charge the field, you know.
他大叫来开辟道路
Yeah, and he's fucking blowing people outta the way.
"大家让开! 大家让开 !"
"Get outta the way! Get outta the way!"
我真不敢相信你有票!
I can't fucking believe you had tickets to that fucking game!
- 你有冲到场上吗? - 我没冲到场上 我不在场
- Did you rush the field? - No, I didn't rush the fucking field. I wasn't there.
- 什么? - 我跟我未来的老婆在喝酒
- What? - No, I was in a bar, having a drink with my future wife.
你错过菲斯克的全垒打 跟一个不认识的女人喝酒?
You missed Pudge Fisk's home run to have a fucking drink with some lady you never met?
对 你该看看她 令人惊艳
Yeah, but you should have seen her. She was a stunner.
- 我才不管他妈的... - 她让整个屋子亮起来
- I don't care if... - Oh, no, no, she lit up the room.
- 西施走进来我也不在乎 - 哦 西施!
- I don't care if Helen of Troy walks into the room. - Oh, Helen of Troy!
那可是重量级比赛啊! 天哪 你朋友都是些什么人?
That's game six! Oh, my God, and who were these friends of yours?
- 他们就这么放过你? - 他们没办法
- They let you get away with that? - They had to.
- 你跟他们怎么说? - 我把票滑过去
- What did you say to them? - I just slid my ticket across the table.
说 "抱歉 兄弟们 我要去找一个女孩"
I said, "Sorry, guys. I gotta see about a girl."
- "我要去找一个女孩"? - 是的!
- "I gotta go see about a girl"? - Yes!
你就那么说? 他们就放过你了?
That's what you said? They let you get away with that?
对 他们看到我认真的眼睛
Oh, yeah. They saw it in my eyes that I meant it.
- 你骗我? - 不 我没骗你
- You're kidding me? - No, I'm not kidding you, Will.
所以我现在不会因为...
That's why I'm not talking right now about some girl I saw at a bar 20 years ago...
当年在酒吧没和她说话而懊悔终生
and how I always regretted not going over and talking to her.
我不后悔跟南茜结褵的18年
I don't regret the 18 years I was married to Nancy.
不后悔为她的病放弃辅导
I don't regret the six years I had to give up counseling when she got sick,
不后悔那最后几年守着重病的她
and I don't regret the last years when she got really sick.
更不会后悔错过球赛
And I sure as hell don't regret missing a damn game.
只是有点遗憾
That's regret.
哇!
Wow!
看到那场球赛还是不错的
Would have been nice to catch that game though.
我不晓得矮冬瓜会击出全垒打
I didn't know Pudge was gonna hit a home run.
我在球场上很有优势
You know, I'm very, very useful on the court.
我很高
I'm extremely tall.
- 你没那么高 - 我会灌篮
- You're not that tall. - I dunk.
我能打NBA吗?
Will I ever play in the N.B.A.?
"绝对可以"
"It is decidedly so." Hmph.
为什么老是待在这边?
Why do we always stay here?
因为比我家好
because it's nicer than my place.
但我从没去过你家
Yes, but I've never seen your place.
我知道
I know.
我几时见到你朋友和哥哥?
When am I gonna meet your friends and your brothers?
嗯 他们不常来这里
Well, they don't really come down here that much.
我可以到南波士顿
I think I can make it to South Boston.
有点远
It's kind of a hike.
是我还是他们见不得人?
Is it me you're hiding from them or the other way around?
- 好 我们去 - 几时?
- All right, we'll go. - When?
不知道 下个礼拜吧
I don't know. We'll go sometime next week.
如过我说不让我见他们 就再也不跟你上床 你怎么办?
What if I said I would not sleep with you again until you let me meet your friends?
我会说 清晨四点半 他们应该醒了
I'd say it's, like, 4:30 in the morning. They're probably up.
天哪 男人真无耻
Oh, my God. Men are shameless.
你们男人就只会用小弟弟思考
If you're not thinking with your wiener, then you're acting directly on its behalf.
仅代表我的小弟弟 向否向你预支?
You bet. And on behalf of my wiener, can I get an advance payment?
不知道 我问问 "前途不明朗"
I don't know. Let's ask. "Outlook does not look good."
- 什么? - 干... 嘿 查克 没事 继续睡
- What? - Fuck the... Hey, Chuck. No. Nothing. Go back to sleep.
"前途"? 你去打NBA才前途不明朗
"Outlook"? That's the same thing that told you you was gonna play in the N.B.A.
没错 所以你最好开始买季票
Exactly, so look out. You'd better start buying some season tickets.
正有此意 我很高 我喜欢穿短裤
Mmm! I plan to. I'm tall. I like wearing shorts.
勾射 勾射 灌篮 灌篮
Hook, hook. Dunk, dunk.
- 你没那么高 - 我有
- You're not that tall. - Yes, I am.
我三分射篮很行
Maybe I'm all about three points.
我就很会打全垒打
I'm all about home runs.
别用运动术语影射
Stop mixing your sporting metaphors.
妖精的老二在猴子屁眼里
A leprechaun's got his dick in the monkey's ass.
摩根跑出来说 "我不介意 我不介意..."
Morgan comes running in, going, "I don't mind it. I don't mind..."
干 你竟挑我们烂醉时带她来
Well, I can't believe you brought Skylar here when we're fucking all bombed and drinking.
我知道 摩根 我们很难得一起喝酒
I know, Morgan. It's a real rarity we'd be all drinking.
我叔叔马帝只要一喝酒 就会狂欢个一年半载
My uncle Marty drinks. He'll go on a bender for six, eight months.
我讲过他开车被拦下来的事没?
Did I ever tell ya what happened to him when he was driving up there and got pulled over?
- 我跟你们讲过的 对吗? - 马帝 嗯
- I told you guys, right? - Marty, yeah.
我来说说马帝叔叔的事 你们应该知道的
Let me tell ya what happened to my uncle Marty, because you oughta know this.
他很喜欢讲故事 每次我到他那里都有新花样
He's always telling stories. Every time we come here he's got another story.
这个我们早就听过了 还是说吧 快讲
But we all heard this one. Go ahead. Say it anyway.
我会讲 多谢 换我发言
I will go ahead. Thanks a lot. Guess I have the floor now.
我叔叔开车回家 对吗?
My uncle Marty's driving home, right?
撞到了树 对吗? 他醉得一塌糊涂 撞得七零八落
Bombed out of his tree, right? Just hammered out of his gourd. Just wrecked.
州警看见 把他拦下来 我叔叔惨了
This state trooper sees him, pulls him over. So my uncle's fucked basically.
州警要他下车走直线
Got him out of the car, trying to make him walk the line.
结果他吐在州警身上 州警确信他超过酒精浓度
He gets out of the car, pukes, and the statie's pretty sure he's over the legal limit.
正要把他戴上手铐送去坐牢
So he's about to throw the cuffs on him and put him in jail.
突然五十码外他妈的一声巨响
All of a sudden, 50 yards down the road, there's this huge fucking boom.
- 州警吓一大跳 转身... - 枪声?
- Statie gets real spooked. He turns around... - He got shot?
不是... 你听过这故事了
No. So... So... You heard this story before.
摩根 停 停
Yeah, Morgan, stop. Stop.
是别人的车撞到树 出事了
Some other guy's car had hit a tree. There was an accident.
总之...
Anyway...
- 那他... - 他妈的闭嘴!
- How could he hear... - Shut the fuck up!
- 你把他惹毛了 - 我要扭断你脖子 闭嘴!
- You're driving him nuts. - I'm gonna break your neck. Shut up!
他跟你说过这故事了
He told you the story once before.
州警跟我叔叔说"站住 别走"
So he tells my uncle, "Stay here. Don't move."
就跑去处理另一起事故
Statie goes running down the road to deal with the other accident.
躺在尿和呕吐物中几分钟后
After a few minutes of just lying in his own piss and vomit,
我叔叔才想到他在那儿干嘛
my uncle starts wondering what he's doing there.
于是站起来开车回家
Gets up, gets in his car and just drives home.
隔天早上我叔叔还昏迷不醒
The next morning my uncle's just passed out.
他听到敲门声
He hears this knocking at the door.
下楼拉开门... 说"什么事?"
So he goes downstairs, pulls the door open... "What?"
敲门的是拦下他的州警
It's the state trooper that pulled him over.
州警说"我操 你明知故问
Statie says, "Fuck you mean, 'What?'
我昨晚拦下你 你逃走了"
You know what. I pulled you over last night is what, and you took off."
叔叔说"我从来没见过你
He's like, "l never seen you before in my life.
我整晚在家 你乱讲什么"
I've been home all night with my kids. I don't know who the fuck you are."
州警说"别装蒜了 到车库"
He's like, "You know who I am. Let me get in your garage."
我叔叔说"什么?" 州警说"带我去你的车库"
My uncle's like, "What?" He said, "You heard me. Let me get in your garage."
我叔叔说"好的" 带他到车库 打开门
He was like, "All right. Fine." Takes him out to the garage, opens the door.
警车就在我叔叔的车库里
And there's... The statie's police cruiser is in my uncle's garage.
他他妈的...
He was so fucking...
他醉到他妈的开错车回家了
He was so fucking hammered he drove the wrong car home.
最屌的是州警好糗...
The best part about it is, the fucking state trooper...
他整晚什么都没做
was so embarrassed he didn't do anything.
开着我叔叔的车挨家挨户找人
He'd been driving around all night in my uncle's Chevelle, looking for the house.
你的故事重点是什么?
All right, Chuck, what the fuck is the point of your story?
他逃跑了就是重点
He got away. That's the point.
- 好 问题是... - 得了 快停下
- Well, question... - Come on. Stop.
- 我在努力阐明一些事情 - 你是在糗他
- I'm trying to clarify something. - You're embarrassing him.
- 你讲的故事没什么道理 - 这个故事有道理
- It doesn't make any sense. - It does make sense,
听故事别问东问西的
if you listen to the story and quit asking questions.
摩根 看这个故事你懂不懂
Well, let's see if you can get this one. I've got a little story for you.
好 一对老夫妻在床上 玛丽和派帝
All right, there's an old couple in bed, Mary and Paddie.
结婚50周年那天他们醒来
They wake up on the morning of their 50th anniversary.
玛丽深情地望着派帝
Mary looks over and gazes adoringly at Paddie.
说 "天哪 派帝
She's like, "Oh, Jesus, Paddie.
你真是一个大帅哥 我爱你
You're such a good-looking feller. I love ya.
我要送你一件礼物
I want to give ya a little present.
你渴望什么我都给你
Anything your little heart desires, I'm going to give it to ya.
你想要什么?
What would ya like?
派帝说 "玛丽 这真是甜蜜的提议
Paddie's like, "Oh, gee, Mary. That's a very sweet offer.
五十年来就少一样东西
Now, in 50 years, there's one thing that's been missing,
我希望你帮我吹喇叭
and, uh, I would like you to give me a blow job.
我想要" 玛丽说 "好"
I would like for it." Mary's like, "All right."
她把假牙拿掉 放进杯子里 然后帮他吹
She takes her teeth out, puts them in the glass. She gives him a blow job.
之后派帝说 "天啊 这就是我最渴望
Afterwards, Paddie's like, "Yeah, geez, now that's what I've been missing.
最美妙 最勾魂摄魄的事!
That was the most beautiful, earth-shattering thing ever!
太棒了 玛丽! 我爱你!
Beautiful, Mary! I love ya!
我能为你做什么吗?"
Is there anything that I can do for you?"
玛丽抬头看着他说 "亲一下"
Mary looks up to him and she goes, "Give us a kiss."
- 噢! - 噢 我的天!
- Oh! - Oh, my God!
- 好恶心 - 不恶心 我听过更恶心的
- That's filthy. - It's not that filthy. I've heard filthy.
- 离我远点! - 好的 再见
- Get off of me! - All right. See you guys later.
保重 比利
All right. Take it easy, Bill.
史凯兰 谢谢你过来
So, Skylar, thanks for coming by.
改变我对哈佛人的看法
Changed my opinion of Harvard people.
别骤下断语 他们跟我不同
You don't want to rush to judgment on that one, because they're not all like me.
我相信 很高兴认识你
Oh. I'm sure. It was nice to meet ya.
- 噢 - 小心 慢慢让开
- Oh. - Take it easy. Slowly back away.
- 快点 兄弟  - 我不知道你要干什么 老兄
- Oh, come on. Brother. - I don't know what you're doing, dude.
- 你要送我们 - 你以为我在干嘛?
- You're giving us a ride. - What the fuck do I look like to you?
- 快点 查克 - 你来步行 车给威尔
- Come on, Chuck. - You're walking, bitch. Will's taking the car.
好 谢了 很感激
All right, thanks, sucker. I appreciate it.
干嘛这么正经
I don't know what you're getting all serious about.
- 你还是要先送我回家 - 这样很不顺路
- You're dropping me off first. - It's really out of the way.
别以为今晚可以外宿...
Oh, okay. Just because you don't have to sleep in your one-room palace tonight...
就屌成这样
don't start thinking you're bad.
等一下 你说要去看你家
Hey, wait a minute. You said we were gonna see your place.
- 今晚不行 - 今晚不行 哪一晚都不行
- Not tonight. - Oh, no, not tonight. Not any other night.
他知道你一看过就会甩了他
He knows once you see that shit-hole he's getting dropped like a bad habit.
但我想见你哥哥
But I wanted to meet your brothers.
不 改天吧
We're gonna do that another time.
好吧
All right.
我需要钥匙
Need them keys.
空服员听到就往走道上冲
The stewardess hears this and goes hauling ass down the aisle.
我喊道 "别忘了咖啡"
I yell, "Don't forget the coffee."
狗屁! 你没那么说
No shit! You didn't say that.
拜托 那是笑话嘛
For Christ's sake, Marty, it's a joke.
- 我认识真的碰到这事的人 - 只是个笑话
- I know someone that actually happened to, Marty. - A joke.
- 杰洛 - 嗨
- Gerry. - Hi.
- 这边很难找吗? - 不会 我搭计程车
- Have trouble finding the place? - No, I took a cab.
提米 这是杰洛 大学同学
Timmy, this is Gerry. We went to college together.
你好 幸会
How you doing? Nice to meet ya.
- 幸会 - 请你喝杯啤酒吧?
- Pleased to meet you. - Can I get you a beer?
不 来杯沛绿雅
Um, no, just a Perrier.
那是法文的苏打水
That's French for club soda.
- 苏打水 好 - 再来几个三明治
- Club soda, yeah. - Couple of sandwiches too.
- 好 - 算在我帐上
- Sure. - Put it on my tab.
你打算要签帐吗?
You ever planning on paying your tab?
要 我这边有中奖彩券
Yeah, chief, got the winning lottery ticket right here.
- 奖金多少? - 一千两百万
- What's the jackpot? - Twelve million.
- 我看不够付 - 够付你的变性手术了
- I don't think that'll cover it. - It'll cover your sex change operation.
- 坚果? - 不 谢谢
- Nuts? - No, thank you.
那么 你想谈谈威尔
So, you wanted to talk about Will.
- 好像很顺利 - 我想是的
- Well, it seems to be going well. - I think so.
你跟他谈过未来没?
Have you talked to him at all about his future?
没谈到那种程度 我们还只是在往事中徘徊
No, we haven't gotten into that yet. We're still banging away at the past.
该开始谈了 许多工作都急着找他
Maybe you should. My phone's been ringing off the hook with job offers.
- 哪种工作? - 尖端科技数学 智囊团
- What kind? - Cutting edge mathematics, think tanks.
威尔的头脑能发挥的地方
The kind of place where a mind like Will's is given free rein.
那真好 但他还没准备好
That's great that there are offers, but I don't really think he's ready for that.
我想你不明白 尚恩
I'm not sure you understand, Sean.
- 我不明白什么? - 来了
- What don't I understand? - Here you go, guys.
- 谢谢 提米 - 谢谢你
- Thanks, Tim. - Yeah, thank you.
这样手指不会拧拧的
Just so you don't get sticky fingers.
提米 你要帮我们吗?
Tim, can you help us?
我们要赌一赌输赢
We're trying to settle a bet.
哦
Uh-oh.
- 听过乔纳斯索克吗? - 当然 被治愈的小儿麻痹症患者
- Ever heard of Jonas Salk? - Sure. Cured polio.
- 听过爱因斯坦吗? - 嘿
- Ever heard of Albert Einstein? - Hey.
杰洛蓝勃呢? 听过吗?
How about Gerald Lambeau? Ever heard of him?
- 没有 - 谢谢
- No. - Thank you, Tim.
- 谁赌赢了? - 我赢了
- So who won the bet? - I did.
这不是我的事
This isn't about me, Sean.
我跟这年轻人比起来不算什么
I'm nothing compared to this young man.
你听过杰洛蓝勃吗?
You ever hear of Gerald Lambeau?
在1905年 有许多以研究宇宙闻名的教授
In 1905 there were hundreds of professors renown for their study of the universe.
但改变世界的却是个
But it was a 26-year-old Swiss patent clerk,
趁闲暇时研究物理的26岁办事员
doing physics in his spare time, who changed the world.
你可以想像如果爱因斯坦...
Can you imagine if Einstein would have given that up...
每天都喝得烂醉的话会怎样
just to get drunk with his buddies in Vienna every night.
我们都会失去一些东西
We all would have lost something.
而提米绝不会听过他
Tim would never have heard of him.
- 非常戏剧化 - 不是
- Pretty dramatic, Gerry. - No, it isn't, Sean.
这孩子有天赋
This boy has that gift.
他只是没方向 我们应该给他
He just doesn't got the direction, but we can give that to him.
杰洛 在60年代 曾有一个密西根大学毕业的年轻人
Hey, Gerry, in the 1960s, there was a young man graduated from University of Michigan.
他的数学很出色
Did some brilliant work in mathematics.
特别是有界集函数
Specifically, bounded harmonic functions.
他到柏克莱当助教 潜力惊人
Then he went on to Berkeley. He was assistant professor. Showed amazing potential.
然后在蒙大拿州赢得竞赛
Then he moved to Montana, and he blew the competition away.
- 好 他是谁? - 泰德卡辛斯基
- Yeah, so who was he? - Ted Kaczynski.
没听过
Haven't heard of him.
- 提米! - 哟!
- Hey, Timmy! - Yo!
- 谁是泰德卡辛斯基? - 邮包炸弹狂
- Who's Ted Kaczynski? - Unabomber.
那就是我要说的
That's exactly what I'm talking about.
- 他需要我们指点方向 - 嗯...
- We gotta give this kid direction. - Yeah...
他能贡献世人 我们能帮他做到
He can contribute to the world, and we can help him do that.
方向是一回事 操纵是另一回事
Direction's one thing. Manipulation's another.
- 尚恩... - 你要让他自己发掘...
- Sean... - We have to let him find...
尚恩 我不是每晚坐在家里绞尽脑汁...
I'm not sitting at home every night twisting my mustache and hatching a plan...
策划怎么摧毁他的人生!
to ruin this boy's life!
我18岁就会做高级数学
I was doing advanced mathematics when I was 18,
然而之后仍旧花了20年才得到菲尔兹奖
and it still took me over 20 years to do something worthy of a Field's medal.
也许他不想照你的想法去做
Maybe he doesn't want what you want.
人生不只是一个他妈的奖章
There's more to life than a fucking Field's medal.
这太重要了 而且这要超越个人立场
This is too important, Sean, and it's above personal rivalry.
等等 我们谈的是这孩子
Wait a minute. Let's talk about the boy.
为何不给他时间想清楚要什么?
Why don't we give him time to figure out what he wants?
很棒的理论 可以为你创造奇迹 是吗?
That's a wonderful theory, Sean. It worked wonders for you, didn't it?
对 你这个自负的混蛋!
Yeah, it did, you arrogant fucking prick!
我很遗憾 很遗憾今天我来了
Oh, I'm sorry. I'm sorry that I came here today.
我是来这是出于好意 我想让你参与这件事
I came here out of courtesy. I wanted to keep you in the loop.
我很高兴能够参与
Nice to be in the loop.
那孩子此刻正在我安排的面谈中
The boy's in a meeting right now I set up for him over at McNeil.
威尔 我不清楚你的意思
Well, Will, I'm not exactly sure what you mean.
我们已经给你职位了
We've already offered you a position.
这年头做事没人不拿酬金的
Nobody in this town works without a retainer, guys.
你们认为找得到 我祝福你们
You think you can find somebody who does, you have my blessing.
但没有人可以像我做得那么好
But I think we all know that person is not gonna represent you as well as I can.
我们已给你年薪八万四加福利
Will, our offer is $84,000 a year.
酬金! 酬金
Retainer! Retainer.
你是要我们现在给你现金?
You want us to give you cash right now?
慢点... 我没那么说
Whoa-ho-ho. Easy... Now, I didn't say that.
这么说来 这种情况下 对你来说
Allegedly, your situation, for you,
如果我口袋里有两百块...
would be concurrently improved if I had...
你们的处境会同时获得改善
$200 in my back pocket right now.
我不认为我能... 赖瑞?
I don't think I can... Larry?
- 我有73块 - 你收支票吗?
- I've got $73. - Will you take a check?
我说你们这种举止相当可疑
Let me tell you something. You're suspect.
对 你们 我不知道你们的声誉怎样
Yeah, you. I don't know what your reputation is in this town,
但耍这种花招
but after the shit you tried to pull today,
我一定会调查
you can bet I'll be looking into you.
关于我们未来的合作
Now, any business we have heretofore,
请和我的律师谈
you can speak with my aforementioned attorney.
再见 先生们
Good day, gentlemen.
在那天到来前 拼命干活吧
And until that day comes, keep your ear to the grindstone.
- 怎么样? - 很好
- How's it going? - Fine.
嗯
Yeah.
好的
Good.
- 要帮忙吗? - 不要!
- Want some help? - No!
给我看一下 我们要去练球场
Come on. Give me one little peek, and we'll go to the batting cages.
不
No.
我一定要念这个 真的很重要
It is actually important that I learn this.
- 对我而言... 真的很重要 懂吗? - 好吧
- It's really important... to me, okay? - All right.
- 那就在这边待一整天? - 有何不可?
- Why don't we just hang out here all day? - Yes, why don't we?
好 多管闲事先生
All right, Mr. Nosey Parker.
既然你打算烦我
Seeing as you're intent on breaking my balls,
- 让我问你一个问题 - 好的
- let me ask you a question. - All right.
你有影像记忆力吗?
Do you have a photographic memory?
不知道 我就是记得 就好比你可以记得你的电话号码
I don't know. I just kind of remember. I mean, how do you remember your phone number?
就是那么简单
You just do.
- 你念过有机化学吗? - 一点点
- Have you studied organic chemistry? - A little bit.
- 为了好玩? - 对 为了找乐趣
- Oh, just for fun? - Yeah, for kicks.
念有机化学会有趣
Yeah, it's so much fun studying organic chemistry.
你疯啦?
Are you mad?
你精神失常吗?
Have you completely lost your mind?
没人会为了好玩念化学 没有必要 尤其对你这种人而言
Nobody studies it for fun. It's not a necessity, especially for someone like you.
- 我这种人? - 对
- Someone like me? - Yeah.
相对公平地把时间分配给练球场和酒吧的人
Someone who divides their time, fairly evenly, between batting cages and bars.
- 我说那没必要 - 噢
- I would hardly say it was a necessity. - Oh.
你知道 哈佛有很聪明的人
You know, there are very smart people here at Harvard.
即便是他们也都得花大力气 因为太难了
Even they have to study, because this is really hard.
然而... 你却如此简单地做到了 我不懂
And yet... you do it so easily. I don't understand.
我不懂你的大脑怎么运作
I don't understand how your mind works.
- 你弹钢琴吗? - 别转移话题
- Did you play the piano? - I want to talk about this.
我在跟你解释嘛 你会弹吗?
No, I'm trying to explain it to you. Do you play the piano?
- 一点点 - 当你看着钢琴 就看到莫札特
- Yeah, a bit. - So when you look at a piano, you see Mozart.
- 我看到筷子 - 好 贝多芬 好吗?
- I see "Chopsticks." - All right, well, Beethoven, okay?
他一看到钢琴 很自然地就会弹
He looked at a piano, and it just made sense to him. He could just play.
- 你在说什么? 你是说你会弹琴? - 根本不会
- So what are you saying? You play the piano? - Not a lick.
望着钢琴 我只看到琴键 踏板和木头
I look at a piano, I see a bunch of keys, three pedals and a box of wood.
但贝多芬 莫扎特... 他们看到钢琴 自然而然就会弹
But Beethoven, Mozart... They saw it. They could just play.
我不会画画 连球都打不好
I couldn't paint you a picture. I probably can't hit the ball out of Fenway.
- 我也不会弹琴 - 但你会一小时内做好化学作业
- And I can't play the piano. - But you can do my O-chem paper in under an hour.
对 我就是有那种才能 就是那么得心应手
Right. Well, I mean, when it came to stuff like that, I could always just play.
我只能解释到这样
That's the best I can explain it.
- 来 我有话告诉你 - 嗯?
- Come here. I have to tell you something. - Huh?
- 我跟你讲一件事 - 噢
- I have to tell you something. - Oh.
那没...
Well...
- 这不公平 - 什么不公平? 什么?
- It's not fair. - What's not fair? What?
我在这边四年了
I've been here for four years,
直到现在才发现你
and I've only just found you.
起码你还是发现我啦
Well, you found me.
- 你醒着吗? - 没有
- Are you awake? - No.
你没睡
Yes, you are.
跟我一起去加州
Come to California with me.
什么?
What?
我要你跟我去加州
I want you to come to California with me.
- 你确定吗? - 确定
- You sure about that? - Oh, yeah.
你怎么知道?
Yeah, but how do you know?
不晓得 我就是知道
I don't know. I just know.
但你怎么会知道?
Yeah, but how do you know?
我知道 因为我感觉得到
I know because I feel it.
- 因为你说的是很严肃的事 - 我知道
- Because that's a really serious thing you're saying. - I know.
下礼拜到了加州...
You could be in California next week...
你可能会发现不喜欢我的地方
and you might find out something about me you don't like.
你会希望你没说过这些话
Maybe you wish you hadn't said that,
但这是无法收回的事
but you know it's such a serious thing you can't take it back.
于是我跟不爱我的人困在加州
Now I'm stuck in California with someone that doesn't really want to be with me,
- 她却希望一切能收回 - 什么? 什么是收回?
- just wish they had a take-back. - A what? What's a take-back?
我不想收回 我只要你跟我去加州
I don't want a take-back. I just want you to come to California with me.
我不能和你去加州...
Well, I can't go to California with you, so...
为什么?
Why not?
一是因为我在这边有工作
Well, one, because I got a job here.
二是因为我住这边
And, two, because I live here.
听着 你不爱我就该告诉我
Look, um, if you don't love me, you should just tell me.
我没说不爱你
I'm not saying I don't love you.
那为什么? 那为什么不去? 你怕什么?
Then why? Why won't you come? What are you so scared of?
我怕什么?
What am I so scared of?
你不怕什么?
Well, what aren't you scared of?
你活在没人挑战的世界里...
You live in this safe little world where no one challenges you...
别随意指摘我的世界怎么样 别随意指摘我的世界怎么样
Don't tell me about my world. Don't tell me about my world.
你只是想跟低下阶层搞一下
You just want to have your little fling with the guy from the other side of town.
然后到斯坦福 你会嫁给你父母认同的...
Then you're gonna go off to Stanford. You're gonna marry some rich prick...
那些有钱的混蛋...
who your parents will approve of...
跟其他富家女坐在一起...
and just sit around with the other trust fund babies...
说你到过贫民窟
and talk about how you went slumming, too, once.
你在说什么? 你为何这么在乎钱?
Why are you saying this? What is your obsession with this money?
我十三岁丧父 继承家产
My father died when I was 13, and I inherited this money.
我每天醒来 都希望能把钱都还给他
You don't think every day I wake up, and I wish I could give it back.
只要能让我多陪他一天 我会毫不犹豫放弃所有财产
That I would give it back in a second if it meant I could have one more day with him.
但我不能 那是我的人生 我面对它
But I can't, and that's my life, and I deal with it.
别把你的害怕推到我身上
So don't put your shit on me when you're the one that's afraid.
我怕? 我怕什么? 我他妈的怕什么?
I'm afraid? What am I afraid of? What the fuck am I afraid of?
你怕我 怕我不爱你
You're afraid of me. You're afraid that I won't love you back.
你知道吗? 我也怕
You know what? I'm afraid too.
但我想试试看 起码我诚实
But fuck it, I want to give it a shot. At least I'm honest with you.
- 难道我对你不诚实? - 不 你的十二个哥哥呢?
- I'm not honest with you? - No, what about your 12 brothers?
好的
All right.
你不能走 不准离开
No, you're not going. You're not leaving.
你想知道什么? 我没有12个哥哥? 我他妈的是个孤儿?
What do you want to know? That I don't have 12 brothers? That I'm a fucking orphan?
- 你不会想听的 - 我并不晓得
- You don't want to hear that. - I didn't know that.
你不会想听我童年被人用香烟烧
You don't want to hear I got fucking cigarettes put out on me when I was little.
- 我不晓得 - 那不是手术
- I didn't know that. - That this isn't fucking surgery.
那混蛋刺伤我 你不会想听这种事 史凯兰!
The motherfucker stabbed me. You don't want to hear that shit, Skylar!
- 我想要听 - 别跟我说你想听!
- I do want to hear that. - Don't tell me you want that shit!
- 因为我想帮你 - 帮我? 什么鬼东西?
- I want to help you. - Help me? What the fuck?
我脸上有写着"请救我"吗?
What do I got, a fucking sign on my back that says, "Save me"?
- 没有 - 我像要人救的样子吗?
- No. - Do I look like I need that?
- 我想跟你在一起... - 别耍我!
- No, I just want to be with you... - Don't bullshit me!
- 我爱你 - 别耍我! 别他妈的耍我!
- I love you. - Don't bullshit me! Don't you fucking bullshit me!
我爱你
I love you.
我要听你说你不爱我
I want to hear you say that you don't love me.
因为如果你说出口...
Because if you say that...
那么我就不再打电话给你...
then I won't call you...
不再出现在你的生命里
and I won't be in your life.
我不爱你
I don't love you.
很多人都无从得知自己的天赋
Most people never get to see how brilliant they can be.
因为找不到相信他们的老师
They don't find teachers that believe in them.
于是他们深信自己很笨
They get convinced they're stupid.
希望你能感激他所做的
I hope you appreciate what he's doing,
因为我知道他很喜欢跟你合作
because I've seen how much he enjoys working with you,
我没有反对你
not against you.
你好 威尔
Hello, Will.
汤姆 拿点咖啡来
Tom, can you get us some coffee?
好的
Sure.
好的 我看看
Now, let's see.
很好 正确
Good. This is correct.
你用了麦克老林公式
I see you used Maclaurin here.
我不知道那玩意叫什么 但是...
Yeah, I don't know what you call it, but...
这样不对
This can't be right.
这会很难堪
This would be very embarrassing.
- 你是否想过... - 我确信是对的
- Did you ever consider... - I'm pretty sure it's right.
听着 我们以后能在尚恩的办公室做心理治疗吗?
Hey, look, can we do this at Sean's office from now on?
我得放下工作过来 坐车很烦
Because I got to knock off work to come here and the commute is killing me.
- 好 可不可能... - 那是对的
- Yeah, sure. Did you think of the possibility... - That's right.
那是对的 把它带回家吧
It's right. Just take it home with you.
麦尼尔的面谈怎么了?
What happened at the McNeil meeting?
我去不了 我有约会
I couldn't go. I had a date.
所以我派我的谈判代表去
So I sent my chief negotiator.
你自己的时间爱干嘛随你
On your own time, you can do whatever you like, Will.
但我安排的会谈
But when I set up a meeting with my associates,
你没出现 就会让我丢脸
and you don't show up, it reflects poorly on me.
- 好 那就别安排了 - 我不会
- Then don't set up any more meetings. - I won't.
我会通通取消
I'll cancel them.
我会亲自给你工作 让你看看外面的世界
I'll give you a job myself. I just wanted you to see what was out there.
或许我不想一辈子做解说员
Maybe I don't want to spend the rest of my fucking life explaining shit to people.
但你可以表示感激吧
I think you could show me some appreciation.
感激? 你知道这有多容易吗?
A little appreciation? Do you know how easy this is for me?
你知道这他妈的有多容易吗? 别他妈的说笑了
Do you have any fucking idea how easy this is? This is a fucking joke.
我很遗憾你不会解... 真的...
I'm sorry you can't do this... I really am...
因为我不想坐在这儿看你摸索 然后搞砸掉
Because I wouldn't have to fucking sit here and watch you fumble around and fuck it up.
这样你就会有更多的时间花天酒地 是吗?
Then you'd have more time to sit around and get drunk instead, wouldn't you?
没错 这完全浪费我的时间
You're right. This is probably a total waste of my time.
你说得对
You're right, Will.
我解不出来 但你会做到
I can't do this proof, but you can.
说到这个 这个世界只有少数人...
And when it comes to that, it's only about just a handful of people in the world...
才能看出你我的差别
who can tell the difference between you and me.
- 我是其中之一 - 我很遗憾
- But I'm one of them. - Sorry.
我也是
Yeah, so am l.
我常希望没遇到你
Most days I wish I never met you,
这样我夜里就能睡得着
because then I could sleep at night.
不用惦记在外面有个像你这样的人
I didn't have to walk around with the knowledge that there was someone like you out there.
我就不必看着你糟蹋天赋
I didn't have to watch you throw it all away.
比尔 等等 听到没?
Bill, hold it. Did you hear that?
摩根!
Morgan!
如果你还敢在我妈房里看A片 我就揍扁你!
If you're watching pornos in my mom's room again, I'm gonna give you a fucking beating!
怎么了 老兄?
What's up, fellas?
摩根 要打手枪在你家里打 脏死了
Morgan, why don't you jerk off in your own fucking house. That's fucking filthy.
我家没录影机
I don't have a V.C.R. in my house.
他妈的我不管
Come on. Not in my glove.
我没用手套
I didn't use the glove.
那是我的小联盟手套
That's my Little League glove.
你要我怎么做?
What do you want me to do?
你怎么搞的?
I mean, what's wrong with you?
操棒球手套啊?
You'll hump a baseball glove?
我没有 我用它清干净
I-I just used it for cleanup.
别在我妈房里打手枪了
Stop jerking off in my mother's room.
- 这屋里还有别台录影机吗? - 真可悲
- Is there another V.C.R. in the house? - It's just sad, bro.
我为什么该为国安局做事?
So why do you think I should work for the National Security Agency?
你将研究尖端科技
Well, you'd be working on the cutting edge.
接触别处看不到的科技
You'd be exposed to the kind of technology you wouldn't see anywhere else,
因为这些都已被列为机密
because we've classified it.
超弦理论 混沌数学 高级算法
Superstring theory, chaos math, advanced algorithms.
破解密码
Code breaking.
那是其中一个层面
That's one aspect of what we do.
得了 那就是你们做的事
Oh, come on. That is what you do.
你们处理八成的情报量
You guys handle 80 of the intelligence workload.
是中情局的七倍大
You're seven times the size of the C.I.A.
我们不喜欢自夸 但你说对了
We don't like to brag about that, Will, but you're exactly right.
我的看法 问题不是:
So the way I see it, the question isn't:
"你干嘛为国安局做事?"
"Why should you work for the N.S.A.?"
而是: "你为何不做?"
The question is: "Why shouldn't you?"
我为何不为国安局做事?
Why shouldn't I work for the N.S.A.?
很难的问题 让我想想
That's a tough one, but I'll take a shot.
若我为国安局做事 国安局的人给我个密码破解
Say I'm working at the N.S.A. and somebody puts a code on my desk.
其他人都束手无策的密码
Something no one else can break.
或许我试了 也破解了
Maybe I take a shot at it and maybe I break it.
我很满意 因为表现良好
I'm real happy with myself because I did my job well.
但也许那个密码是位于北非或中东的叛军位置
But maybe that code was the location of some rebel army in North Africa or Middle East.
他们发现后轰炸叛军藏身地
Once they have that location, they bomb the village where the rebels are hiding.
陌生的 毫无瓜葛的一千五百人因此丧命
Fifteen hundred people that I never met, never had no problem with, get killed.
然后政客高呼 "派遣海军陆战队维护当地秩序"
Now the politicians are saying, "Send in the Marines to secure the area,"
他们才不在乎
because they don't give a shit.
被射杀的不会是他们的子女
It won't be their kid over there getting shot,
他们也算参了军 因为他们都加入了后备部队
just like it wasn't them when their number got called because they were in the National Guard.
而在那边中弹的南区孩子
It'll be some kid from Southie over there taking shrapnel in the ass.
回国后发现他以前工作的工厂...
He comes back to find the plant he used to work at...
被移转到他去打仗的国家
got exported to the country he got back from,
害他中弹的敌人抢了他的饭碗...
and the guy who put the shrapnel in his ass got his old job...
因为那个人一天工资不到一元
because he'll work for 15 cents a day and no bathroom breaks.
最后他发现他会上战场...
Meanwhile, he realizes the only reason he was over there in the first place...
是为了得到该国的廉价原油
was so we could install a government that would sell us oil at a good price.
好让石油公司利用战争恐慌抬高国内油价
Of course, the oil companies used a skirmish over there to scare up domestic oil prices.
小赚一番 但两块五一加仑有个屁用
A cute little ancillary benefit for them, but it are'nt helping my buddy at 2.50 a gallon.
他们得花时间把石油运回国
They're taking their sweet time bringing the oil, of course.
或许还请了一个酗酒船长
Maybe they even took the liberty to hire an alcoholic skipper,
他爱喝马丁尼 玩冰山滑雪
who likes to drink martinis and fucking play slalom with the icebergs.
不久他撞上冰山 原油外漏...
It are'nt too long till he hits one, spills the oil...
杀光北大西洋的海洋生物
and kills all the sea life in the North Atlantic.
现在我朋友失业 也开不起车
So now my buddy's out of work, he can't afford to drive,
他走路去面试...
so he's walking to the fucking job interviews...
这很难受 因为炮弹片让你慢性出血
which sucks because the shrapnel in his ass is giving him chronic hemorrhoids.
与此同时 他饥寒交迫 因为每次想吃东西
Meanwhile, he's starving, because every time he tries to get a bite to eat,
唯一的特餐就是...
the only blue plate special they're serving...
北大西洋鳕鱼
is North Atlantic scrod with Quaker State.
那么我会怎么想? 我有更好的点子
So what did I think? I'm holding out for something better.
干 我干脆射杀我朋友算了
I figure, fuck it. While I'm at it, why not just shoot my buddy,
把他的工作留给敌人
take his job, give it to his sworn enemy,
提高油价 轰炸村庄 打死小海豹
hike up gas prices, bomb a village, club a baby seal,
吸食大麻 加入后备部队?
hit the hash pipe and join the National Guard?
我还可因此被选为总统
I can be elected president.
- 你感觉孤单吗? - 什么?
- You feel like you're alone? - What?
你有心灵伴侣吗?
Do you have a soul mate?
我有... 说清楚点
Do I have a... Define that.
能够和你匹敌的人
Somebody who challenges you.
- 我有查克 - 不 查克是你的家人 现在还因为你车祸受伤躺在医院
- Uh, Chuckie. - No, Chuckie's family. He'd lie down in fucking traffic for you.
我指的是敞开你心扉 触动你心灵的人
I'm talking about someone who opens up things for you, touches your soul.
- 我有... 我有... - 谁?
- I got... I got... - Who?
- 有很多 - 说出来
- I got plenty. - Well, name them.
莎士比亚 尼采 佛斯特 奥康纳 康德 洛克...
Shakespeare, Nietzsche, Frost, O'Connor, Kant, Pope, Locke...
很棒 他们都死了
That's great. They're all dead.
- 对我而言 他们没死 - 你无法和他们对谈
- Not to me they're not. - You don't have a lot of dialogue with them.
你不能回应他们
You can't give back to them, Will.
- 除非你有仙丹 - 对 那就是我所说的
- Not without some serious smelling salts and a heater. - That's what I'm saying.
如果你不踏出第一步...
You'll never have that kind of relationship in a world...
你绝不会有那种关系
where you're always afraid to take the first step,
因为你只看到负面的事
because all you see is every negative thing ten miles down the road.
- 你要摆出教授架子了? - 少跟我来这套
- You gonna take the professor's side on this? - Don't give me a line of shit.
- 没有 - 我不想做那个工作
- No. - I didn't want the job.
不关工作的事 我不管你是否为政府工作
It's not about the job. I don't care if you work for the government.
但你能随心所欲 不受束缚
But you can do anything you want. You are bound by nothing.
你热爱什么? 想要什么?
What are you passionate about? What do you want?
有人一辈子砌砖...
There are guys who work their entire life laying brick...
让孩子拥有像你现在的机会
so their kids have a chance at the opportunities you have here.
- 我可没要求这机会 - 不
- I didn't ask for this. - No.
不 你与生俱来就有 别逃避说: "我可没要求"
You were born with it, so don't cop out behind: "I didn't ask for this."
- 什么叫逃避? 砌砖哪里不对? - 没有
- What do you mean, cop out? What's wrong with laying brick? - Nothing.
我为别人家盖房子 有什么不对
There's nothing wrong. That's somebody's home I'm building.
对 我爸砌砖 好吗?
Right. My dad laid brick, okay?
他拼命干活让我受教育
Busted his ass so I could have an education.
没错 那是可敬的行业
Exactly. That's an honorable profession.
修车哪不对?
What's wrong with fixing somebody's car?
因为我的工作 别人得以上班 这是很光荣的事
Someone will get to work the next day because of me. That's honor in that.
是的 是很光荣
Yeah, there is, Will. There is honor in that.
搭40分钟火车...
There's honor in taking that 40-minute train ride...
让大学生上课有干净的环境也很可敬
so those college kids could come in in the morning and their floors are clean.
- 他们的垃圾箱空了 这才叫真正的工作 - 对
- And their wastebaskets are empty. That's real work. - That's right.
对 是很可敬 相信你选择这份工作
And that's honorable. I'm sure that's why you took that job.
正是为了这份荣耀
I mean, for the honor of it.
我只是有个小问题 你到哪里都能做工友
I just have a little question here. You could be a janitor anywhere.
为何挑中全世界一流的科技学府?
Why did you work at the most prestigious technical college in the whole fucking world?
夜里偷偷地解算...
Why did you sneak around at night and finish other people's formulas...
世上只有两个人会的方程式?
that only one or two people in the world could do and then lie about it?
我看不到其中的荣耀
because I don't se a lot of honor in that, Will.
你真正想做什么?
So what do you really wanna do?
我想当牧羊人
I wanna be a shepherd.
真的?
Really?
我想搬到纳旭 买块地皮放羊
I wanna move up to Nashua, get a nice little spread, get some sheep and tend to them.
- 也许你该那么做 - 什么?
- Maybe you should go do that. - What?
要自慰的话 何不回家弄条湿毛巾搞?
You know, if you're gonna jerk off, why don't you just do it at home with a moist towel?
- 你在赶我? - 对 他妈的滚出去
- You're chucking me? - Yeah, get the fuck outta here.
- 不 不 不 时间还没到 - 时间到了
- No, no, no, time's not up yet. - Yeah, it is.
- 我不走 不 - 你在逃避我的问题 你在浪费我的时间
- I'm not leaving. No. - You're not gonna answer, you're wasting my time.
我以为我们是朋友
I thought we were friends.
- 游戏时间结束了 懂不? - 你为什么赶我走?
- Playtime's over, okay? - Why are you kicking me out?
你想教我人生大道理? 看看你 糟老头
You're lecturing me on life? Look at you, you fucking burnout.
- 是什么让你过下去? - 跟你合作
- What winds your clock? - Working with you.
你的心灵伴侣在哪? 你要谈心灵伴侣吗? 她在哪?
Where's your soul mate? You wanna talk about soul mates? Where is she?
- 死了 - 对 她他妈的已经死了
- Dead. - That's right. She's fucking dead.
你就不敢再为人生下赌注了?
She fucking dies and you just cash in your chips and you walk away?
- 起码我玩过一把 - 那你输了 输得很惨
- At least I played a hand. - You played a hand and you lost. You lost a big fucking hand.
有些人即便输得那么惨还是会再下注
Some people will lose a big hand like that and have the sack to ante up again.
看着我 你想要什么?
Look at me. What do you wanna do?
你和你那些屁话 对每个人你都有狗屁答案
You and your bullshit. You got a bullshit answer for everybody.
却答不出来我提出的那么简单的问题
But I ask you a very simple question and you can't give me a straight answer,
因为你不知道
because you don't know.
再见 躲猫猫
I'll see ya, Bo-peep.
- 去你的 - 你是牧羊人
- Fuck you. - You're the shepherd.
牧羊人
Shepherd.
混蛋
White little prick.
我只是想 你知道的
I just wanted to, you know, um,
趁你还没走打电话给你...
call you up, uh, before you left, um...
我正在面试谈工作
I've been taking all these jobs interviews and stuff,
我不会只当营造工人
so I'm not gonna be just a construction worker.
你知道我并不在乎
Well, you know, I never really cared about that.
是的
Yeah.
我爱你
I love you.
威尔?
Will?
你保重
You take care.
Someone's always coming around here
再见
- Trailing some new kill - Bye.
Says, I seen your picture on a
Hundred-dollar bill
What's a game of chance to you
In this world
Of real skill
So glad to meet ya
Angeles
Picking up the ticket shows there's money to be made
Go on, lose the gamble
That's the history of the trade
Did you add up all the cards left to play
To zero
And sign up with people
Angeles
Don't start with me trying
威尔
Will
威尔 好了! 做完了!
Will, that's it! We're done!
我在你办公室 那孩子没来
I'm sitting in your office and the boy isn't here.
都五点十分了
Well, it's ten past 5:00.
迟到一小时十分
An hour and ten minutes late.
I can make you satisfied in everything
他如果没出现 我会向法院如实提出报告..
Well, if he doesn't show up and I file a report saying he wasn't here...
他去坐牢 我不会愧疚的
and he goes back to jail, he won't be on my conscience.
Now be coming true
好 很好
Okay. Fine.
怎么了?
What's up?
谢谢
Thanks.
啊! 真爽
Ah! God, that's good.
你马子怎么样?
So how's your lady?
她走了
Ah, she's gone.
走了? 到哪里去了?
Gone? Gone where?
医学院 加州的医学院
Med school. Medical school in California.
- 真的? - 嗯
- Really? - Yeah.
- 几时的事? - 一礼拜前
- When was this? - It was, like, a week ago.
好烂
That sucks.
那些会谈几时搞完?
So, uh, when are you done with those meetings?
大概是我过了21岁之后的那个星期
I think the week after I'm 21.
他们要给你工作吗?
They gonna hook ya up with a job or what?
对 他妈的往后50年要呆坐在房间里做无聊的算术
Yeah, fucking sit in a room and do long division for the next 50 years.
可能会攒不少钱
Nah, probably make some nice bank though.
我会成为他妈的实验室老鼠
I'm gonna be a fucking lab rat.
好过这鬼东西 离开这里
Better than this shit. Way outta here.
干嘛要走?
What do I want a way outta here for?
我他妈的下辈子都要住这儿
I mean, I'm gonna fucking live here the rest of my life.
我们会成为邻居 会当爸爸
You know, be neighbors. You know, have little kids.
一起带孩子们去球场打小联盟
Fucking take them to Little League together up Foley Field.
你是我的死党 所以别误会
Look, you're my best friend, so don't take this the wrong way.
但20年后你如果还住在这儿
But in 20 years if you're still living here,
到我家看球赛
coming over to my house to watch the Patriots games,
还在盖房子 我他妈的会杀了你
still working construction, I'll fucking kill ya.
那不是恐吓 我认真的 我会宰了你
That's not a threat. That's a fact. I'll fucking kill ya.
你在胡扯什么?
What the fuck are you talking about?
- 你拥有我们没有的天赋 - 拜托!
- Look, you got something none of us have. - Oh, come on!
为何大家都这么说? 难道是我对不起自己吗
Why is it always this? I fucking owe it to myself to do this or that.
- 我就是不想那么做 那又怎么办? - 不 不 不 去你的 你没有对不起自己
- What if I don't want to? - No, no, no. Fuck you. You don't owe it to yourself.
你对不起我
You owe it to me,
因为我明天醒来五十岁了
because tomorrow I'm gonna wake up and I'll be 50,
还在干这种事
and I'll still be doing this shit.
无所谓
That's all right. That's fine.
而你已拥有百万奖券
I mean, you're sitting on a winning lottery ticket.
却窝囊的不敢兑现 狗屁
You're too much of a pussy to cash it in, and that's bullshit.
因为我会不惜一切交换你所拥有的
because I'd do fucking anything to have what you got.
其他人也是
So would any of these fucking guys.
你再待20年是侮辱我们
Be an insult to us if you're still here in 20 years.
窝在这里是浪费你时间
Hanging around here is a fucking waste of your time.
- 你懂什么 - 我不懂?
- You don't know that. - I don't?
- 你不懂 - 我不懂 我告诉你我懂什么
- No. You don't know that. - Oh, I don't know that. Let me tell you what I do know.
我每天到你家接你
Every day I come by your house, and I pick you up.
我们出去喝酒笑闹 那很棒
We go out and have a few drinks and few laughs, and it's great.
但你知道我一天中最棒的时刻是什么?
You know what the best part of my day is?
只有十秒: 从停车到走到你家门口这段时间
It's for about ten seconds: from when I pull up to the curb and when I get to your door.
因为每次我敲门 都希望你不在家
because I think maybe I'll get up there and I'll knock on the door and you won't be there.
不说 "再见" 或是 "明天见" 什么都没有 你就是走了
No "good-bye," no "see ya later." No nothing. You just left.
我懂得不多 但我很清楚
I don't know much, but I know that.
真是乱来 尚恩
This is a disaster, Sean.
我让你参与 是要你帮这孩子
I brought you in here because I wanted you to help me with the boy,
- 不是赶走他 - 我知道怎么应付这孩子
- not to run him out. - I know what I'm doing with the boy.
我不管你跟他有什么默契!
I don't care if you have a rapport with the boy!
我不在乎你们花我的钱开心
I don't care if you have a few laughs, even at my expense.
- 但你敢破坏我的事看看 - 破坏?
- But don't you dare undermine what I'm trying to do here. - Undermine?
这孩子目前很脆弱
This boy is at a fragile point right now.
我了解他很脆弱 他还有些问题
I do understand. He is at a fragile point. He's got problems.
他有什么问题? 当工友或坐牢会比较好吗?
What problems does he have? That he's better off as a janitor, in jail?
跟一群智障在一起会比较好吗?
Better hanging out with a bunch of retarded gorillas?
你想他为什么那么做? 你晓得为什么吗?
Why do you think he does that? You have any fucking clue why?
他能应付问题 应付工作 显然也应付得了你
He can handle the problems. He can handle the work. He obviously handled you.
听我说 他为何躲避?
Listen to me. Why is he hiding?
为何不信任人?
Why doesn't he trust anybody?
因为他生下来遇到的头一遭事
Because the first thing that happened to him,
就是他被本应该最爱他的人遗弃
he was abandoned by the people who were supposed to love him the most.
别跟我讲佛洛伊德的屁话
Don't give me that Freudian crap.
他为什么跟你所谓的智障混?
Why does he hang out with those retarded gorillas, as you call them?
因为如果他叫他们扁你 他们会照办
Because any one of them, if he asked them to, would take a bat to your head.
- 那叫做义气 - 是喔 很感人
- That's called loyalty. - Yeah, that's very touching.
他应付谁了? 他在别人先离开他之前就把别人赶走
Who's he handling? He pushes people away before they have a chance to leave him.
那是防卫心理 好吗?
It's a defense mechanism, all right?
他因此孤独了20年
For 20 years, he's been alone because of that.
你现在逼他 事情会重演
If you push him right now, it's gonna be the same thing all over again.
我不会让他重蹈覆辙
I'm not gonna let that happen to him.
- 别那么做 - 什么?
- Don't you do that. - What?
别让他认为放弃没关系 或者失败也没关系
Don't infect him with the idea that it's okay to quit, that it's okay to be a failure.
因为绝对有关系 尚恩!
Because it's not okay, Sean!
如果你是气我成功 或是气我...
And if you're angry at me for being successful, for being what you could have been...
- 我没气你 - 不 你有气我
- I'm not angry at you. - Oh, yes, you're angry at me.
憎恶我 但我不会因为比你成功而向你赔不是
You resent me, but I'm not gonna apologize for any success I've had.
你气我做到你本来能做到的事!
You're angry at me for doing what you could have done!
你扪心自问 尚恩... 扪心自问...
But ask yourself, Sean... Ask yourself...
你要威尔也有那种感受? 你要他感觉像失败者?
if you want Will to feel that way... if you want him to feel like a failure?
你这个自大狂!
You arrogant shit!
我不去同学会的原因 是因为受不了你的眼神
That's why I don't come to the goddamn reunions, because I can't stand that look in your eye.
- 那种屈尊难堪的眼神 - 得了 尚恩
- That condescending, embarrassed look. - Oh, come on, Sean.
你认为我失败 我有自知之明
You think I'm a failure. I know who I am.
我为自己感到骄傲 那是自觉的选择 我没搞砸!
I'm proud of what I do. It was a conscious choice. I didn't fuck up!
你和你朋友认为我很可怜
And you and your cronies think I'm some sort of pity case.
你和你那些狗屁课程 你老是提自己的菲尔兹奖
You and your kiss-ass chorus following you around going, "The Field's medal!"
你怎么还是这么怕失败?
Why are you still so fucking afraid of failure?
你是嫉妒我有奖章吗? 天哪 我回家拿给你 送给你好了
It's about my medal, isn't it? Oh, God, I could go home and get it for you. You can have it.
把奖章他妈的塞进你自己的屁眼里
Shove the medal up your fucking ass, all right?
因为我不在乎你的奖章
because I don't give a shit about your medal,
因为我在你还没当上数学之神以前就认识你了
because I knew you before you were a mathematical god,
早在你满脸青春痘 思乡 不知要尿在床的那一头的时候
when you were pimple-faced and homesick and didn't know what side of the bed to piss on.
是 你过去现在都比我聪明
Yeah, you were smarter than me then and you're smarter than me now.
那么你的人生变成这样别怪我
So don't blame me for how your life turned out.
我没怪你! 这跟你无关!
I don't blame you! It's not about you!
你这数学混球! 是关于那孩子!
You mathematical dick! It's about the boy!
他是个好孩子! 我不会看着你像现在糟蹋我这般糟蹋他
He's a good kid! And I won't see you fuck him up like you're trying to fuck up me right now.
我不会看着你让他也感觉是失败者!
I won't see you make him feel like a failure too!
- 他不会失败! - 但你如果逼迫他! 如果驱使他!
- He won't be a failure! - But if you push him! If you ride him!
我能有今天成就是逼出来的
I am what I am today because I was pushed and because I learned to push myself.
他不是你! 你听懂没!
He's not you! You get that!
我待会再来
I can come back.
不 进来 我正要走
No, come in. Uh, I was just leaving.
这是他和我之间的陈年往事
A lot of that stuff goes back a long way between me and him.
你知道 跟你无关
You know. Not about you.
那是什么?
What is that?
你的档案 我要送回去给法官评估
This is your file. I have to send it back to the judge for evaluation.
你不会让我失败吧?
Oh. Hey, you're not gonna fail me, are you?
里面怎么写?
What's it say?
- 你想看吗? - 为什么?
- Wanna read it? - Why?
你有过那种经验吗?
Have you had any, uh, experience with that?
20年的辅导 我看过很惨的事
Twenty years of counseling. Yeah, I've seen some pretty awful shit.
你有那方面的经验吗?
I mean, have you had any experience with that?
- 个人的? - 是的
- Personally? - Yeah.
我有
Yeah, I have.
我想肯定不好
It sure are'nt good.
我爸是酒鬼
My father was an alcoholic.
烂醉如泥
Mean fucking drunk.
他喝醉回家就想打人
He'd come home hammered, looking to whale on somebody.
我激怒他以保护妈妈和弟弟
So I'd provoke him so he wouldn't go after my mother and little brother.
他若晚上带工具回来就精彩了
Interesting nights when he wore his rings.
他把扳手
He used to just put a wrench,
棍子和皮带摆在桌上
a stick and a belt on the table.
- 然后说: "选一个" - 我会挑皮带
- Just say, "Choose." - Well, I gotta go with the belt there.
我通常挑扳手
I used to go with the wrench.
为什么是扳手?
Why the wrench?
因为是"操他的"
because fuck him, that's why.
- 你养父? - 对
- Your foster father? - Yeah.
这么说来 是不是威尔有"依附情结"?
So, uh, what is it, like, Will has an attachment disorder?
就是这么回事?
Is it all that stuff?
害怕被遗弃?
Fear of abandonment?
那是我跟史凯兰分手的原因吗?
Is that why I broke up with Skylar?
- 我不晓得你们分手了 - 我提出的分手
- I didn't know you had. - Yeah, I did.
- 想谈吗? - 不想
- You wanna talk about it? - No.
威尔 我知道的不多
Hey, Will, I don't know a lot.
但你看到这个没? 这些事?
You see this? All this shit?
这不是你的错
It's not your fault.
是的 我知道
Yeah, I know that.
看着我 孩子
Look at me, son.
- 这不是你的错 - 我知道
- It's not your fault. - I know.
这不是你的错
No. It's not your fault.
我知道
I know.
不 不 你不知道 这不是你的错
No, no, you don't. It's not your fault.
- 嗯? - 我知道
- Hmm? - I know.
- 这不是你的错 - 好的
- It's not your fault. - All right.
这不是你的错
It's not your fault.
- 这不是你的错 - 别整我
- It's not your fault. - Don't fuck with me.
这不是你的错
It's not your fault.
别整我好吗? 别整我
Don't fuck with me, all right? Don't fuck with me, Sean, not you.
这不是你的错
It's not your fault.
我的天...
My God...
我的天! 真对不起! 我的天!
My God! I'm so sorry! My God!
去他们的 好吗?
Fuck them, okay?
- 有何贵干? - 我是威尔杭汀 我来谈工作
- Can I help you? - Yeah, I'm Will Hunting. I'm here about a position.
你能座一下稍等片刻吗?
Could you just have a seat for a moment?
对 大厅里是有一位杭汀先生
Yes, there's a Mr. Hunting in the lobby.
你选择哪一个?
Which one did you take?
麦尼尔那边 教授帮我安排的工作之一
I was over at McNeil. It's one of the jobs the professor set me up with.
我还没告诉他 但我和老板谈过...
I haven't told him yet, but I went down there and talked to my boss...
新老板人好像不错
My new boss. He seemed like a good guy.
- 那是你要的吗? - 对 我想是吧
- Is that what you want? - Yeah, you know, I think so.
做得好 恭喜
Well, good for you. Congratulations.
谢谢
Thanks.
时间到了
Time's up.
就...就这样了? 我们结束了?
So that's... So that's it? So we're done?
对 就这样
Yeah, that's it.
你结束了 自由了
You're done. You're a free man.
我要你知道 我...
Well, um, I just want you to know, Sean, that...
不客气
You're welcome, Will.
希望我们保持联络
So, you know, I hope we keep in touch, you know.
我也希望
Yeah, me too.
我会旅行一阵子 会有点难 但...
I'll be traveling around a bit. It'll be a little hard, but, uh...
不过我有答录机 我会查看留言
I've got an answering machine at the college I'll be checking in with.
拿着 我的号码
So, here's the number.
你打来 我会马上回电话
You call that. I'll get back to you right away.
你知道 我要再下注...
Yeah, you know, I figured I'm just gonna...
看看这次赌到什么
put my money back on the table and see what kind of cards I get.
做自己真心想做的事 你就没事了
You do what's in your heart, son. You'll be fine.
- 谢谢你 尚恩 - 呃...
- Thank you, Sean. - Uh...
谢谢你 威尔
Thank you, Will.
这违反医师病人关系吗?
Hey, does this violate the patient-doctor relationship?
除非你抓我屁股
Naw. Only if you grab my ass.
- 保重 - 你也是
- Take care. - You too.
嗯
Yeah.
嘿
Hey.
祝你好运 孩子
Good luck, son.
两瓶啤酒
Two beers.
什么事? 你们去了吗?
What's up? Did you guys go?
没有 我得劝退他
No. I had to talk him down.
- 你怎么不约束他? - 摩根有一堆屁话
- Why didn't you yoke him? - Little Morgan's got a lot of scrap to him.
天天有人想扁他
People try to whip his ass every week.
- 他还不让步 - 讲我什么坏话?
- Fucking kid won't back down. - What are you saying about me?
我跟你讲话吗? 干你屁事
Was I talking to you? None of your fucking business.
- 帮我弄瓶啤酒 - 我叫了两瓶!
- Go get me a beer. - I ordered two beers!
- 浑蛋 - 干嘛 贱货?
- Hey, asshole. - What, bitch?
- 生日快乐 - 以为我们忘了吗 贱货?
- Happy birthday. - Thought we forgot, huh, bitch?
- 快点! - 我去 我去
- Come on! - I'm going. I'm going.
谁先?
All right. Who's first?
- 混蛋! - 谁先?
- Come on, motherfucker! - Who's first?
丹尼男孩
Oh, Danny boy
你的礼物
Here's your present.
- 快点 兄弟 - 什么?
- Come on, bro. - What?
你的新工作要在剑桥来回
Well, we knew you had to get back and forth to Cambridge for your new job.
我不会每天载你 所以...
I knew I wasn't gonna fucking drive you every day, so...
- 摩根想给你买免票证 - 我没那么说!
- Morgan wanted to get you a "T" pass. - That's not what I was saying!
但你21岁了
But, uh, you're 21 now.
可以合法喝酒 我们想最好的礼物就是车子
You're legally allowed to drink, so we figured the best thing for ya was a car.
- 喜欢吗? - 这是...
- How do you like it? - This is like...
我这辈子看过最丑的车
It's the ugliest fucking car I've ever seen in my life.
- 快 兄弟 - 你们怎么弄的?
- Come on, brother. - How'd you guys do this?
我和比尔一起搜括零件
You know, me and Bill scraped together the parts,
摩根每天出去乞讨零钱
and Morgan was out panhandling for change every day.
车身都是我搞的
I had the router to do all the bodywork.
我他妈的也出力了
Yeah, I have a fucking job, too, brother.
他烦了我两年要工作 我总得帮他把车的问题解决了
Guy's been up my ass for two years about a job. I had to let him help with the car.
你终于有工作了 摩根?
So you finally got a job, huh, Morgan?
- 有过一个 现在又没了 - 是什么工作?
- Yeah, had one. Now I'm fucked again. - So what is it?
- 除草工人吗? 什么工作? - 这他妈的是6缸发动机
- A lawn mower? What do ya got? - It's a straight fucking six.
我和比尔重新打造引擎
Me and Bill rebuilt this engine ourselves here.
这是辆好车 引擎不错
It's a good car. The engine's good. Engine's good.
- 21岁生日快乐 - 21岁生日快乐
- Happy 21, Will. - Happy 21, brother.
嗨
Hi.
进来
Come on in.
尚恩 我...
Sean, l, um...
我也是 奇洛
Me too, Gerry.
那就好
Yeah. Good.
听说你要请假
I heard you're taking some time.
对 我想旅行一阵子 或许写书
Yeah. Travel a little bit, maybe write.
去哪里?
So where are you going?
印度 中国和巴尔的摩
India and China and Baltimore.
噢
Oh.
你知道几时回来吗?
You know when you'll be back?
知道 我前两天收到传单
Oh. I got this flyer the other day.
上面说半年后72年毕业的那届要开同学会
It says, uh, class of '72 is having a reunion in six months.
是的 我也收到一张
Yeah, I got one of those too.
你来吧 我请你喝酒
Why don't you come? I'll buy ya a drink.
那种场合的酒是免费的
The drinks at those things are free.
我知道 奇洛 我是在讽刺
I know, Gerry. I was being ironical.
- 哦 - 现在喝一杯怎么样?
- Oh. - How about a drink right now?
好主意
Yeah. It's a good idea.
走 这杯我请
Come on. This one's on me.
- 我这边有会中奖的彩券 - 噢!
- I got the winner right here, pal. - Oh!
对 就是这张
Yes, sir, this is the one.
通往天堂的票
This is my ticket to paradise.
你知道彩券中奖的机率吗?
Do you know what the odds are against winning the lottery?
- 多少? 四比一? - 三千万比一
- What? Four to one? - About 30 million to one.
但我还是有机会 知道吗?
I still have a shot, you know?
对 跟现在被闪电击中的机率一样
Yes, just about as big chance as you being hit by lightning here on the staircase right now.
那也有可能 我是说 3200万 如果你看看...
It's a possibility too. I mean, 32 million. If you look at the size...
威尔!
Will!
威尔?
Will?
他不在
He's not there.
I'll fake it through the day
尚恩 如果教授问起工作的事
Sean, if the professor calls about that job,
跟他说抱歉 我要去找个女孩
just tell him sorry, I had to go see about a girl.
威尔
Will.
小混蛋 偷学我的台词
Son of a bitch. He stole my line.
To take its toll and in having a lot
Of nothing to do
Do you miss me
Miss misery
Like you say you do
I know you'd rather see me gone
Than to see me
The way
That I am, when I am
In the life anyway
Next door TV's flashing through
Frames on the wall
It's a comedy
Of errors, you see
It's about taking a fall
To vanish into
Oblivion
It's easy to do
And I try to be
But you know me I come back
When you want me to
Do you miss me
Miss misery
Like you say you do
Gonna find my baby Gonna hold her tight
Gonna grab some afternoon delight
My motto's always been When it's right, it's right
Why wait until the middle of a cold, dark night
When everything's a little clearer in the light of day
And we know the night is always gonna be here anyway
Thinking of you is working up an appetite
Looking forward to a little afternoon delight
Rubbing sticks and stones together make the sparks ignite
And the thought of rubbing you is getting so exciting
Skyrockets in flight
Afternoon delight
Started out this morning feeling so polite
I always thought a fish could not be caught who didn't bite
But you got some bait a-waiting and I think I might
Like nibbling a little afternoon delight
Skyrockets in flight
Afternoon delight
Be waiting for me, baby when I come around
We can make a lot of loving before the sun go down
Thinking of you is working up an appetite
Looking forward to a little afternoon delight
Rubbing sticks and stones together make the sparks ignite
And the thought of rubbing you is getting so exciting
Skyrockets in flight
Afternoon delight
Aft